<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Death unstung a sermon preached at the funeral of Thomas Mowsley, an apothecary, who died July, 1669 : with a brief narrative of his life and death : also the manner of Gods dealings with him before and after his conversion : drawn up by his own hand and published / by James Janeway ...</title>
            <author>Janeway, James, 1636?-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12831002</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12831002</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94327</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94327)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 385:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Death unstung a sermon preached at the funeral of Thomas Mowsley, an apothecary, who died July, 1669 : with a brief narrative of his life and death : also the manner of Gods dealings with him before and after his conversion : drawn up by his own hand and published / by James Janeway ...</title>
                  <author>Janeway, James, 1636?-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 166, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman,and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1]-[8] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mowsley, Thomas, d. 1669.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94327:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94327:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Death Unſtung. A SERMON Preached at the Funeral of <hi>THOMAS MOWSLEY,</hi> An Apothecary, who died <hi>July</hi> 1669.</p>
            <p>With a Brief Narrative of his Life and Death: Alſo the manner of Gods dealings with him before and after his Converſion: Drawn up by his own hand; and Publiſhed</p>
            <p>By <hi>James Janeway,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>O Death, where is thy ſting?</p>
               <p>Come and hear all ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my ſoul,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 66.</hi> v. <hi>16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop near the <hi>Lame-Hoſpital</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> at the Chyrugions Arms. 1669.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94327:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94327:2"/>
            <head>TO My Beloved HEARERS, Eſpecially Thoſe of the Younger ſort, Grace and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men, Brethren and Fathers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD that made your ſouls, ſets a very high value upon them; and Chriſt that bought them, though they coſt his heart-blood, thought them worth his purchaſe, and that eternal glory or miſery that is prepared for ſouls ſpeaks them not to be inconſiderable. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this account it's impoſſible that you and I ſhould uſe too much diligence in the ſecuring theſe
<pb facs="tcp:94327:3"/>ſouls; for this cauſe the Miniſters of Chriſt can eaſily over-look priſons, baniſhment and faggots, ſo that they may but be inſtrumental for the ſaving of ſouls, and delivering them from the wrath to come: This I hope is the ground that I am carrying on in this enſuing Diſcourſe: This may ſpeak when I may not, when I cannot. I might give many reaſons of my appearing thus in print. I might tell the world of the deſires of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that by reaſon of the multitude could only ſee, but not hear. I might ſpeak of the want of time to deliver the fourth Part of what is here preſented to you. I might tell you of the importunity of ſome of the young men that would gladly write after this Coppy: But I muſt profeſs all this would have ſignified little with me; did I not find by that account which ſome give of the work of grace upon their hearts, that the Lord hath owned my poor papers formerly: Among others, that poor penitent Murtherer, <hi>Thomas Savage,</hi> which makes me not without hope that the ſame Spirit which breathed life into my other Writings, may pleaſe alſo to give a bleſſing to theſe. I will not ſtand now to anſwer the Objections that may be made againſt the Publication of this Sermon. I never met with this,
<pb facs="tcp:94327:3"/>that it is impoſſible that it ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to the ſalvation of a ſoul, and therefore I think the coſt anſwerable. I muſt confeſs, had it not been for a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Caution or two, I ſhould have eaſed you of the trouble of reading, and my ſelf of writing this Epiſtle. The firſt is this; Be not offended if you find in the Young Mans Evidences ſome expreſſions that may ſound ſomewhat harſh, and ſome tautologies; remember that they are word for word from his own papers, as he wrote them haſtily: conſider alſo that he was but young, and a ſervant too; ſo that it ſeems almoſt incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible that one that had ſo much buſineſs, ſhould be able to redeem ſo much time as to do what he did of this nature. Secondly, I would it might be a little conſidered what a hurry I was in when this task was laid upon me, and how little time to peruſe my own Coppy; I beg you therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly to over-look many miſtakes. As for you, my dear friends, I ſuppoſe a pardon is eaſily granted. As for others, ſcorn not holineſs, contemn not the future bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make ſure of happineſs in the life to come, and then I can eaſily bear your ſlighting of me. Young Men, I may be bold with you; I charge you as you value
<pb facs="tcp:94327:4"/>the comforts of another life, forget not what an excellent example this precious Brother of yours gave you. Read this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe with ſeriouſneſneſs, and let it be read again in your lives. Brethren, you are my Joy and Crown, and if you ſtand faſt, I live. O make not my boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing void! How can I bear to think that any of you ſhould periſh? For Gods ſake, and for your ſouls ſake, falſifie that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>A Young Saint, and an Old Devil.</hi> Brethren, my hearts deſire is, that I may ſee you all with that bleſſed Saint at the right hand of Chriſt. Remember, your ſands run apace, and you are haſting into Eternity. O make ſure of that which will ſtand you in ſome ſtead when you die! O ſecure ſomewhat to live comfortably upon in another world! let your lives beſpeak you perſons reſolved for Chriſt, and Heaven upon any terms. Let your loyns be alwaies girt, and your lamps be burning. Whatch ye, be ſtrong; quit you like men. Remember, Chriſt, Heaven and Glory are before you. Sit not ſtill till you are ſafe in the boſom of Chriſt. Conſider that many ſet out fair and look as if they were bound for <hi>Zion,</hi> and yet founder in the way. I ſay again, make ſure: Sirs, I expect ere long to paſs upon
<pb facs="tcp:94327:4"/>Eternity; let me beg of you as you hope for our good meeting in another world, that you make Religion your buſineſs, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get every day nearer Heaven. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour not only to be Chriſtians, but ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, experienced, and examplary Chriſtians; that ſo you may prove the glory of your generation, the credit of Religion, and the Joy of gray-headed Saints. Sirs, you are now my hope; your-love, zeal and union, my comfort; go but on at this rate, and you are made for ever. Know this, now the eyes of the world will be upon you; nay, that which is more, the eye of God is upon you, and will take notice how you improve ſuch a Providence as this. I beſeech you look about, and let the world underſtand that you are not nominal Chriſtians, but real Saints. Will any of you ſend me ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the grave? ſhall I loſe my hopes, and comforts, and you your ſouls? can you eaſily forget what was the practice of this Young Man? do you remember what was the uſual ſubject of his diſcourſe? did you not obſerve how holily, meekly and diligently he ſerved his great Maſter? is there no weight in a Crown of Glory? is there no deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs in happineſs? is it a ſmall thing to live in the ſociety of God, Saints and
<pb facs="tcp:94327:5"/>Angels? I am perſwaded you think theſe things conſiderable. Well then, act as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that long for poſſeſſion; which that all of you may enjoy, is, and ſhall be the prayer of one that deſires not to count his life dear ſo he may but finiſh his courſe with joy, and meet you with comfort hereafter;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Janeway.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>July 28. 1669.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94327:5"/>
            <head>Death <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtung.</head>
            <head>A Funeral SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 14.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, write, bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from hence-forth; yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is none of the leaſt works of a Miniſter of Chriſt to diſparage ſin, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage holineſs, to ſet Life and death before our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to preſent (as much as in us lies) Heaven and Hell to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94327:6"/>their view, and to perſwade them to a wiſe and ſpeedy choice; that when theſe Houſes of Clay ſhall be laid in the duſt, they may be ſecured of an Habitation, not made with hands, that is, Eternal with God in the Heavens. The Apoſtle in this Chapter doth both, in the 10. <hi>Verſe</hi> he tells us what a Draught is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the implacable Enemies of Chriſt: they ſhall drink off the Wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture, into the Cup of his Indignation, and they ſhall be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Fire and Brimſtone, in the preſence of the Holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb. The wicked may drink, roar, and ſwagger, they may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Members of Chriſt, becauſe they dare not ſo madly venture upon the Eternal diſpleaſure of God, as they do, and ſell their precious Souls for a moments joy, and make light of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: but let them know, that for all theſe things God will bring them to Judgment; an Eternity of intolerable ſorrowes muſt pay for their ſhort plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. And hence it is the ſerious Chriſtian, that makes it his buſineſs to avoid this dreadful miſery, is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94327:6"/>that he doth not act irrationally and madly, if the ſcorn and contempt of the wicked World doth not frighten him; upon this account he patiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to any puniſhment, rather than he will hazard the loſs of his Soul, and be miſerable for ever; that word for ever ſticks much in his mind, let the wicked laugh and be merry, let them pleaſe themſelves in his ſorrows, he knows 'tis but a little while, and all will be mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their minds changed; he is willing to ſtay for his happineſs and joyes, till he comes to another World; and he doth not envy the wicked what they do enjoy, let them make the beſt of it as long as they can, and boaſt of their pleaſures when they ſee themſelves wrapt up in Flames: The unſeen world, which moſt forget, is always in the Saints eye; and if he may but live happily there, he paſſeth not if he run thorow reproaches, injuries, and a thouſand Deaths, to that glorious and endleſs life. Here is the reaſon of the Saints patience, this makes him judge it no folly to keep the Commandements of God, and the faith of Jeſus. In the 13. <hi>Verſe,</hi> the Apoſtle comes to ſpeak a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94327:7"/>word of encouragement, not only to the ſuffering Saints of that Age, but for the ſupport of all that ſhould be honoured with ſuch ſervice, as to ſeal the truths of Chriſt with their blood. <hi>And I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto me, write bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord from h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nceforth; yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them.</hi> In the words you may take notice of two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Propoſition.</item>
               <item>2. The Confirmation of that Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Propoſition; in which we may obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Predicate, bleſſed.</item>
                  <item>2. The Subject, the dead.</item>
                  <item>3. The reſtriction and limitation of the Subject, which dye in the Lord.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Confirmation of this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.
<list>
                  <item>1. They reſt from their labours.</item>
                  <item>2. Their works follow them.</item>
                  <item>3. The Perſon affirming this, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is further cleared.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By the manner of this Delaration, it was by a voice from Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94327:7"/>
               <item>2. By the ſpecification of the Perſon to whom it was ſpoken; ſaying, unto me.</item>
               <item>3. By the particular note of Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Write.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Doctrine which I ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of from theſe words, is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> That whatever miſeries a Saint may meet with in this Life, at Death he ſhall be happy; or in the words of the Text, <hi>That they are bleſſed which dye in the Lord.</hi> In the Proſecution of this Obſervation; I ſhall,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Enquire what it is to dye in the Lord.</item>
               <item>2. I ſhall prove that ſuch are bleſſed.</item>
               <item>3. I ſhall ſhew wherein their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth conſiſt.</item>
               <item>4. I ſhall make ſome Application.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall enquire what it is to dye in the Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Neg. <hi>They which make it their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to do what they can againſt God, while they live, are not like to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed when they dye.</hi> They which live like Devils, are not like to dye like Saints: Are there not a Generation in the World who act for the Devil with all their might; and count all that time loſt, which is not ſpent in his ſervice; which make
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94327:8"/>a jeſt of Damning, and are as merry within a ſtep of theſe devouring flames, as if Hell and a Tavern were alike? Do they not carry themſelves, as if they could not make haſt enough to miſery, and make ſure enough of Damnation? How do they wound and ſtab their own Souls, and let flye againſt the Almighty? How contemptible a thing is Heaven, and how ridiculous is the very name of Holineſs to them? They are of the ſame mind of thoſe, which <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks of: <hi>Job.</hi> 21.14. They ſay unto God, depart from us; for we deſire not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy ways. And who is the Lord, that I ſhould hearken to him? And if a compaſſionate Miniſter of Chriſt beſeech them with all the tenderneſſe that he can for his Soul, to bethink themſelves a little what theſe things may end in at laſt, and to conſider what a dreadful thing it is to fall into the hands of a living God; how are his perſwaſions rejected with contempt, and his pitty recompenſed with ſcorn? And may I not ſay of moſt wicked Men, they do flye in the Faces of them that would tell them of their danger, and do what they can to deliver them from it? And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94327:8"/>yet for all this how well are they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with their own condition, and laugh at the godly, as if it were a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and mad thing to ſtrive to go to Heaven, and the trueſt happineſs to be miſerable for ever? O who would imagine, that any living ſhould be thus lamentably beſotted! Tell them of Hell, 'tis as much as their life is worth; they had rather hazard the feeling of it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, than bear the hearing of it here. They fear a little diſgrace among Men more than the contempt of God: They chooſe rather to be under the weight of God's wrath, than the leaſt affront from a Man. Talk to them of Glory, Heaven, and a Kingdom, they are light and trivial things with them; they had rather hear of a Whore, a Tavern, or Play; and yet theſe Monſters muſt be Sainted, and do more confidently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a bleſſed Eternity after a life of wickedneſs, than ſome of the dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God do: but if ſuch as theſe ever come to Heaven without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, then the Word of God is falſe: Doth not that ſay, <hi>That the wicked ſhall be turned into Hell?— Tribulation and anguiſh upon every, one that doth evil,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94327:9"/>and there is no peace, ſaith my God to the wicked.</hi> The Devil himſelf may as well expect to ſhake off his Chains, and be reſtored to his loſt Glory, as they. O be not deceived, as you Sow ſo you muſt Reap; do not hope that you may do the Devils work, as long as you can, and that then God ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you with Salvation: no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: You may more rationally expect, that God ſhould for your ſake pull the Sun out of the Firmament, than that he ſhould remove holineſs out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and bring Hell in its place. If wicked Men will pleaſe themſelves with their own Deluſions, and look for Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtill, they muſt thank themſelves, when they ſee how infinitely they are diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; but I leave theſe as deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to convince them of their folly, till Judgment and Flames make them to underſtand it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>All, that live upon the goodneſs of God here, are not like to be bleſſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death.</hi> There is a vaſt difference between common and ſpecial mercies: many partake richly of God's common bounty, that have not the leaſt intereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his love; God gives this World often
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94327:9"/>times to his greateſt Enemies, he gives Glory in an other World, to none but his Friends and Children: Nay, let me ſpeak it freely (I am ſure I have Chriſt and Scripture to warrant what I ſay) That they which gain this World with their neglect of Heaven, ſhall at their Death loſe both: Many receive tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mercies, that ſhall never enjoy Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. <hi>Job</hi> 21.9. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25. O how greatly are they miſtaken, who think that Earl, Lord Knight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are words of any ſignificancy after Death; that hope that their honours here will procure them any real reſpect hereafter; that reckon Gold and Silver will go currant in that Country! Many that would be counted Perſons of ſome depth and wiſdome, make a World of ſtir about trifles, that drive a great Trade for that which is next to nothing, and that lay in no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Proviſions, than Gravel, Clay, or Dung, when they are bound for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and yet how do they bleſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſay I am rich, and increaſed in Goods, and have need of nothing: Soul take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry? They think they make a very wiſe bargain, when they ſell their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94327:10"/>God, and Heaven, for a little of that which ſome call Riches; not conſidering that a few Hours experience may make them know, though it may be, not cure this miſtake. O that I could but bring my hearers out of this Deluſion! O that their apprehenſions were but rectified, and that they might know the real worth of things and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons! O that I could but bring down the price of ſublunary things, and raiſe the things of that other World to their true worth! Conſider that that holineſs, as meanly as you think of it, is the moſt excellent thing; that that is the greateſt Riches, and Man's higheſt dignity: God knows no difference between a Lord and a Beggar, a Prince and a Subject; He is no reſpecter of Perſons. If there be any difference, it lies here, that God hath more wrath in ſtore for them that had greater ingagements, and better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to ſerve him than other had. I pitty the poor Lords of the World! and I am confident, he that knows the worth of Chriſt, and the nature of his own Soul, can't much envy them; they ſwell like Bladders upon Water for a Moment, and God blowes, and where
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94327:10"/>are they? Now indeed they reckon themſelves very ſecure, and their houſes are free from fear, neither is the Rod of God upon them, they take the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brel, and Harp, and rejoyce at the ſound of the Organ. <hi>Job</hi> 21. They think them Fools that can ſpare their Riches, and want their greatneſs, ſo they may but have an eſtate in inviſibles, and ſecure an Inheritance that will laſt for ever; Theſe are the Men that hate ſeriouſneſs: and holineſs, which is the beauty of Earth and Heaven too, is undervalued by them. And how can they expect ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity ſhould be delightful to them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, when it is abhorred now? how can they look for Heaven when they dye, when they thought it not worth their minding while they lived? No, no, verily, they have their reward, they have now their good things, and much good may they do them. O let me rather gain Chriſt at Death, though I looſe all beſides, than poſſeſs Ten Worlds here, and after all loſe my Soul. Could the mighty ones of the World, have but one Hours diſcourſe with one of their Brethren in Hell, I believe their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments would be hugely altered, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94327:11"/>they would ſoon tell them, that Riches and Honours, and whatſoever elſe moſt Men do purſue, let it be what it will below Chriſt, will yield them but little happineſs and comfort in another world. Riches profit not in the Day of wrath: Do but read, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19, 25. I am the larger, that if poſſible, I might prevent miſtakes, in matters of Eternal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>There are Thouſands that ſeem to have a far better title to this bleſſedneſs, that will fall ſhort of it: and they are Profeſſors,</hi> that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the Name of the Lord. Not all that are called, yea, and eſteemed Chriſtians, are like to have any great benefit by Death. To be <hi>Chriſtned,</hi> and to be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are two things: not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that weareth Chriſt's Livery ſhall have his Wages. O how many Millions are there that have no better ſhelter, than a meer Name to themſelves, from the wrath of God! Is it not more than poſſible to hear, read, pray, and to be eſteemed a Saint, and yet to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry everlaſtingly? How many ſeeming Saints ſhall gain nothing at Death, but a thorow knowledge of their own folly?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94327:11"/>And if to know what God's anger is, be an advantage, when there is no eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of it; and if to have their hearts wounded, when there is no Cure to be had, be any profit; and if to be quite freed of Conſcience ſearching Miniſters be a happineſs when they are out of the reach of their help or pitty; then ſuch may be eſteemed bleſſed: but if all this will but make the Flame hotter, then I leave any ſerious Perſon to judg, whether it doth not concern Men and Women to look after better ſecurity, than this amounts to. Did you ever well ſtudy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21? I hope you will believe Chriſt, though you will not me; read that Scripture, and what ſaith Chriſt? O conſider ſeriouſly, that to be an Heir of Glory is no ſuch light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as moſt judge it to be. To be born to a Crown, and a Kingdome, and to have a good title to it, is a dignity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; but a Mad-man in Chains and Rags, may ſay he is a King, or a Lord. O pleaſe not your ſelves with fanſies. Sickneſs and Death is coming, and then you will know better, whether I had not ſome reaſon to be earneſt with you in this matter. I am moſt afraid of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94327:12"/>confident <hi>Phariſee,</hi> that truſts in his poor ſorry Prayers, and his own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; O that I could but ſhake him and his hopes, before Death and Judgment doth it. O that I could but perſwade him to maintain a jealouſie over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to ſearch and try his Heart, and to bring himſelf to the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and not to be ſatisfied, till he findes that he hath got more than ever any Hypocrite yet had, or can have. The beſt of God's Children are moſt ſuſpicious of themſelves, and afraid of their own deceitful hearts. Do but ſee how <hi>David</hi> carrieth it, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. What is his great requeſt, that he muſt have granted, or he can't be ſatisfied; Is it not that God would deliver him from miſtakes in matters of everlaſting conſequence? ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.80. Pardon this tediouſneſs upon theſe things, if moſt of the Profeſſors of the World did not ſplit upon theſe Rocks, I ſhould paſs theſe things over with ſilence.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>All that dye quietly, are not happy after Death.</hi> It's no unuſual thing for the wicked to carry their falſe peace with them to the Grave. I have heard indeed many poor People boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94327:12"/>of their deceaſed Friends, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves, to think how happy they were, <hi>Becauſe they dyed like Lambs.</hi> (to uſe their own expreſſion) Alas, alas, how many thouſands are there that dye like Lambs, that are but Swine, and have the Devil's Brand upon their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads! It's dangerous arguing from peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples carriage upon a Death-bed, what their ſtate is in another World; ſuch is the hardneſs of Mens hearts, ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the ſearedneſs of their Conſciences, and ſo great the ſubtilty of Satan, that many are carried very quietly to Hell, and fear nothing till they feel; and are not brought to their ſenſes, till unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able horror and anguiſh doth it: And on the other ſide, how many of the precious Sons of <hi>Zion</hi> have ſeat in a Cloud? how many of the dear Children of God may go out of the World tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a painful Death? are not their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuals ſometimes impaired, their reaſon Clouded, and their Bodyes upon the Rack? and yet in a moment they feel themſelves ſwallowed up of that Glory, and the doleful antecedents of their happineſs did but make their reſt more ſweet, and welcome, and put an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94327:13"/>accent upon their bliſs. The truth of it is, it hath not a little puzled ſome, as well as <hi>David,</hi> to conſtrue God's diſpenſations, to ſee the wicked dye quietly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.4. and the godly to have a ſtrange Death; but God will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolve this Riddle: and I think it were no very difficult thing for a ſerious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Man, to give himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſatisfaction in this buſineſs. May not the wicked dye quietly, becauſe his Conſcience is quite ſeared, and he may perſwade himſelf that he hath made an agreement with Death and Hell? may he not hope that there is no ſuch place as Hell; or if there is, that it is tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? may he not make himſelf believe, that the Word of God is not true, and inviſibles are all but fanſies? or that God is ſo merciful, as that he will not damn him? and many ſuch things the Devil helps his Servants with, that ſo his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice may not be diſparaged, and that he may have the better advantage to tempt others. There is much alſo in the nature of the Diſeaſe; and it may be God may try his own Children with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute pains, and let Sathan buffer them, to manifeſt the excellency of his Power,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94327:13"/>and their Grace, to try others of his Children, whether for all this they will ſerve him; and ſome Perſons of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable attainments, and great experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, while in health, may have ſome conſiderable Tryals upon a Death-bed, that poor Chriſtians (which were ready to fear, becauſe they had not their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, that therefore they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all) might ſee that great Saints have their Tryals, as well as they; but I ſhall be far briefer in other things.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſhew you who they are, that are bleſſed at their Death, and to give them a brief Deſcription of thoſe which dye in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>They are ſuch, who are made thorowly to underſtand, that they were ſometimes quite dead in ſins and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſses, that they were Aliens from the Common-wealth of Iſrael, and strangers to the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>They are Perſons which are convinced of that miſery of ſuch a ſtate,</hi> and made to know, that if they dye in their ſins, they muſt be buried in Flames.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this they are out of love with their moſt beloved ſins,</hi> and count that which was their life, joy,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94327:14"/>and pleaſure, to be a very Death, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Hell, whereupon they ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in good earneſt againſt ſin, as the greateſt evil in the World; they believe now, <hi>That if they live after the Fleſh they ſhall dye, but if through the Spirit they mortifie the deeds of the Fleſh, they ſhall live.</hi> Upon this account, they uſe all the means that they can to get their corruptions weakned, an inward prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, Divine Life: Now he begins to act them, which is as contrary to Sin, as Heaven to Hell, a Spirit of ingenuity reſtrains them, <hi>How ſhall they do this, and ſin againſt God?</hi> They now ſee ſin in its colours, as it is contrary to the beſt good, God; they can ſee its killing and damning Nature, in the Agonies and Sufferings of Chriſt, and they feel the doleful effects of ſin in their Soul and body; both, and upon this account they can ſay, what have I to do with Vanity any more, Shall I ſtill hug this Serpent? ſhall I ſtill Sail with this <hi>Jonah</hi> in my Veſſel? and ſhall I after all this keep this Dalilah in my Boſom? No; but, O that I could hate it Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more than I do. There is an enmity raiſed in the Soul againſt ſin,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94327:14"/>which can't be ſatisfied, till it ſee the Death of Sin; now this is a Perſon that is fit for Death, and Death, it will (as you ſhall hear afterwards) do him a World of kindneſs in ſhewing him the Heads of all his Enemies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>An other quality of this Perſon, which is like to make ſuch a bleſſed end, is this, he is one that is dead to the World.</hi> Faith hath diſcovered a better Country to him, it hath ſpyed that new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and thoſe bleſſed Regions: and now the Soul thinks the World ſcarce worthy of a ſerious thought, or look; he takes himſelf to be a kind of Priſoner here, and the whole World but a Dungeon, if compared with that ſtate of liberty and glory; he now joyns with <hi>David,</hi> and ſays, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none upon Earth that I can deſire beſide thee.</hi> This, is the Man that is like to be a gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by Death; he who contemns Earth, and makes Heaven his choice, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver finde himſelf a loſer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Another property of the Man which ſhall be bleſſed at Death, is this, he is one, that takes Chriſt for life and happineſs.</hi> Time was indeed, he was of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94327:15"/>an other mind, ſin was his delight, and none ſo deſpicable in his Eye, as Chriſt; but God, in free and rich grace, hath taken away the Scales from his Eyes, and healed him of his miſerable blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and let him ſee ſuch a lovelineſs in the Lord Chriſt, as that now he is able to ſay, none but Chriſt, none but Chriſt; <hi>He is altogether lovely.</hi> He is now quite out of love with himſelf, neither his righteouſneſs, nor any thing is lovely now, but Chriſt; and will not that Soul be bleſſed, when it comes to have its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires accompliſhed? he that counts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth the having, except Chriſt, and for Chriſt, can't be miſerable, when he is lodged ſafe in his imbraces.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>He that makes it his buſineſs to live to Chriſt, to him to dye ſhall be gain.</hi> God is often times better, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver worſe than his word: And hath he not made many promiſes to them that diligently ſeek him? Hath he not ſaid that their labours ſhall not be in vain in the Lord? The Chriſtian is running, and he ſhall at laſt obtain the Prize, the Crown he fights for, he ſhall have; fear not Chriſtian, quit thy ſelf bravely, win it and wear it; what though it be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94327:15"/>up in Cypreſs? its beauty ſhall not be Vailed long. What though Death with his cold and dirty hand ſet it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy head? it will ſit as neat, and as faſt, as an Almighty hand can make it. What though the Veſſel be toſt and broke? it ſhall come ſafe with its Rich Lading, to the deſired Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn not. O you fooliſh World, theſe ſpiritual Merchants, till you know what their returns are, when their burden is deliver'd; but imitate them, till you can finde a more glorious Prize, than Heaven, a better happineſs than God can give, and a Kingdom that will laſt longer, than Eternity: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.14.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>They which are willing (if called to it) to do, or ſuffer any thing for Chriſt, ſhall inherit this bleſſedneſs.</hi> He that is willing to dye for Chriſt, ſhall live as long as Chriſt lives, in happineſs, and reſt: 'tis not for nothing that <hi>Paul</hi> makes no great matter of bonds, ſcorns at threatnings, and triumpheth in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; the finiſhing his courſe with joy makes all go down ſweetly, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. The Primitive Chriſtians were no Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks, and yet with what patience, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94327:16"/>and joy, did they ſuffer, what the malice, and wit of Men, and Devils could inflict? and now they enjoy the fruit of their labours, the ſalvation of their Souls, and that is not all, but they receive their Palms, Robes and Crowns, ye more peculiar badges of God's Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions; <hi>Loe, thus ſhall it be done to the Perſons, whom the Lord delighteth to honour!</hi> This 'tis to be impriſoned, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, or dye for Chriſt. Rejoyce, O ye ſuffering Saints, and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven! to you it is given, not only to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but alſo to ſuffer; this Fire is but to purifie, and to make you Veſſels more fit for your Maſters uſe, this dirt caſt upon you, is but to ſcower and make you more clean; this knocking, rubbing, and hewing, is but to furbiſh and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh you, that you may be more ſtately Pillars, in the Temple of your God. Fear not Men, nor Devils: the greateſt hurt that they do you, is to fill your Sailes, and to bring you more ſpeedily to your Port.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>They which long for the coming of Chriſt, and their being with him, that can ſay, I have waited for thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94327:16"/>O God, now let thy Servant depart in peace:</hi> In a word, that can bear their abſence from Chriſt, only upon thoſe terms, that they may bring honour to him in this life, and perſwade Souls to be in love with him, and may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental for the ſetting up his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhaking the Kingdom of Sathan, and weakning the intereſt of Hell in the World. Theſe, O theſe are your brave Souls, that are out of Gun-ſhot: Death can neyer ſurprize them, they ſtand always with their Loines girt, and their Lamps burning. And if the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom ſhould make the Mountains to quake, with the ratling of his Charri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, and the Hills to tremble at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Majeſty, and the Heavens themſelves to ſhrivel into nothing, by the glory of his coming, yet they, (O bleſſed Souls!) and they only would break forth into a Song of Triumph, and Eternal Halleluj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hs; Who would not be a Saint? ſure none, but a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or a fool: Do the World under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what theſe things mean! Do they indeed believe how much the higheſt of them all, are below the meaneſt, and loweſt Childe of God? Thus I have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94327:17"/>ſhown you who are the Subjects of this bleſſedneſs. I know I forget time, but it goes well may you and I get but this bleſſedneſs ſecured, and ſpend a happy Eternity.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that I propoſed to ſpeak to, was to prove, that ſuch as theſe are (in ſpight of Hell) ſhall be bleſſed; and becauſe in the fore going diſcourſe, this hath been touched upon, I ſhall but very briefly run over theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>God ſaith, they ſhall be bleſſed, and therefore they ſhall;</hi> when the great Perſecutors have been hunting for their prey, and hope to roaſt what they have got, and ſeed themſelves with the hopes of the content and pleaſure, that they ſhall enjoy; nay, when they ſhall beg with tears for the bleſſing, they ſhall be fruſtrated, denyed, curſed, and hear that heart-rending reply, they have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the bleſſing before you came, 'tis now too late, yea, and they ſhall be bleſſed. Might I not heap up a World of promiſes, the leaſt of which clear a Saints title to this bleſſed, inheritance? time would fail me, if I ſhould but read
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94327:17"/>one in Forty; what is the meaning of that <hi>Eſ.</hi> 57.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Job</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They feel ſomewhat of this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this World, therefore they ſhall have it compleated in another.</hi> How oft do the Saints feel their Souls tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſenſe of divine pleaſures? How many earneſts do they receive of the purchaſed poſſeſſions? How many warm refreſhing Raies of Divine love break in upon their Soul, ſo that they would not exchange one Hours comfort for all the joys that ever the wicked en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, could they all be united in one, and their duration be Eternal? Have I not with much comfort ſeen ſome of thoſe triumphing Saints rejoycing, when others would have mourned? Have I not heard them talk of their ſweet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, the very mention of which, is more reviving to a ſpiritual hearer, than the higheſt pleaſures that the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualiſt is capable of. Sometimes in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er their ſouls even get into the boſom of God, and the great God and Man have a bleſſed intercourſe, the Soul lets out it ſelf to God, and God lets out his love to the Soul. Sometimes in a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94327:18"/>meditation the Heart is glowing, and the Fire burns, and ere it is aware, it is lifted above the World, yea, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it ſelf too: What elſe is this, but the clear demonſtration of the reality of inviſibles? Can meer fancies thus tranſport Men? Muſt they not believe their own experiences? Can that joy, which is the reſult of faith and love, and comes in from the promiſes; and that in a way of duty, and cloſe walking with God, Can that be a deluſion? Will the ſpirit of truth witneſs to a lye? Will goodneſs it ſelf put a cheat upon poor Creatures, and that in a matter of ſuch vaſt conſequence, as Eternity? Can we conceive, that he which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us not to deceive our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſhould deceive us? Shall any that calls himſelf a Chriſtian, entertain ſuch blaſphemous apprehenſions of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Jehovah?</hi> Well then, if it be ſo, that Children of God love ſolid and unexpreſſible joys, many times even on this ſide Glory; Doth not this then prove, that hereatter they ſhall be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and that beyond the apprehenſions of Men, and Tongue of Angels? For the Saint in his greateſt dimenſions, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94327:18"/>enjoyments, and talleſt ſtature on this ſide the Grace, is but a Childe, a Dwarf, a Worm, in compariſon of what he will be, the next moment after his diſſolution: For the proof of this, you may read over theſe, and other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>May I not bring in the wicked themſelves, as witneſſes of the Saints happineſs, and their own miſery,</hi> the Saints wiſdom, and their folly? what elſe is the meaning of <hi>Balaam</hi>'s wiſh? Why ſhould he be ſo deſirous to dye the death of the Saint, and to have his latter end like his, if he were not thorowly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of this, that holineſs were no madneſs, piety no fancy, and religion no deluſion? What is it that makes thoſe, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.8. to cry out ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunately; Give us of your Oyl, for our Lamps are gone out. I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that all the Reprobates in Hell, will one Day juſtifie the Children of God for their ſeriouſneſs, and wiſh a thouſand times, that they had had their ſcornes, loſſes, torments: It is no unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual thing for them, which have to do with dying Perſons, to hear them cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94327:19"/>out with anguiſh, when their time is ſpent, and their ſands are run out, O you are happy, O that I were but in the condition of the pooreſt, and miſerableſt Saint upon Earth O that I had but prayed with fervency, heard with ſeriouſneſs, and minded my Soul in good earneſt! Happy are they that have not all their work to do in a dying Hour, O happy are they that have ſome Cordial to comfort them in a time of ſuch diſtreſs, O, a Chriſt, a Chriſt, ten thouſand Worlds now for that Chriſt, which I deſpiſed! Theſe are things we are acquainted with. Well then, our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies themſelves being Judges, an <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite</hi> indeed is a Perſon of true worth, and without controverſie, his eſtate is, and ſhall be comfortable, bleſſed, and glorious.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>How great are the abſurdities, that elſe would follow?</hi> Would not the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil boaſt that he hath done more for his followers, than Chriſt hath done for his? Would it not follow that Saints are the moſt miſerable fools in the World? then it would be to no purpoſe to deny ones ſelf, to fight with Beaſts at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to bear the contradiction of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94327:19"/>ſinners; then Chriſt dyed for nothing, or hath done his work by the halves; then there is no credit to be given to the Bible, God is worſe than his word, and the Scripture promiſes are falſe; then <hi>Paul</hi>'s confidence was madneſs, and his boaſting made void; then all preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a cheat, and the Miniſters of Chriſt are Impoſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and the wicked are in the right: then <hi>David</hi> would have better reaſon to ſay, he hath cleanſed his hands in vain, and that his frequent devotions were to no purpoſe, and his Songs at Mid-night, but the dotages of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant fanſie, and hours which were ſpent in Prayer and Meditation, were purely loſt. What ſaiſt thou to this, O Chriſtian? Would not this be ſad news indeed, if all thy hope ſhould come to this? But be of good cheer, this is the doctrine which the Devil and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters do preach; as long as God is true you ſhall not be deceived, as long as he is happy you ſhall not be miſerable, and till Hell hath got above Heaven, you are well enough. Go on therefore reſolutely, and let nothing daunt thee, 'tis but yet a little while, and you ſhall ſee all this, and more than this a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94327:20"/>times made good to thee. Fear not, 'tis God who hath ſpoken it, and he commanded his Servant <hi>John</hi> to write, and Jeave it upon Record, <hi>That they which dye in the Lord are bleſſed, and they ſhall reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The next thing which I promiſed to ſpeak to, was, to ſhew wherein the bleſſedneſs of departed Saints doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; But what work am I now about? Who is ſufficient for theſe things? What Tongue can utter the leaſt part of that Glory? What Heart imagine its tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent excellency? And what Ears can bear it? ſhould ſuch a one as <hi>Moſes, Enoch,</hi> or <hi>Elias</hi> come ſparkling in his Robes, in the habit of a glorified Saint, and ſhould he but tell you what a ſight he hath ſeen, what melody he hears, what imployment he is ingaged in, what poſſeſſions he enjoys, where would he endure it? I am perſwaded, if in this mortal ſtate, God ſhould let in the Soul the hundreth thouſandth part of that Glory, which Saints enjoy in Heaven, it would in a moment ſink a Man, and make ſuch Bodies as ours now are wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to duſt. I have ſeen a great many
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94327:20"/>fine things in my time, I have heard of more, but I can eaſily imagine more than ever all the Princes of the Earth, in their greateſt ſplendour enjoyed; and yet here I am at a loſs, and no wonder: For it is beyond the reach of Saints and Angels in Heaven fully to conceive what their own happineſs is, and I believe it is no ſmall part of their joy, that they ſerve a Maſter, who loveth to out-doe, not only deſerts and expectations, but even the imaginations of his Creatures. How then can ſuch a poor Worm as I am, mannage ſuch a work as this is? becauſe I can't ſay all, muſt I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and paſs this over with ſilence and admiration? becauſe this is a great deep, which our Plummet can't fathom, an Ocean that hath no ſhoar, ſhall we therefore never ſail in it? God forbid. O may it be my work in time, and to Eternity to praiſe that infinite, bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs excellency that is in my God. Though theſe are matters, which one would think ſhould command attention and affection both, yet if we conſult the lives of all, yea the higheſt experiences of the beſt, notwithſtanding theſe things are ſo frequently inculcated, and ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94327:21"/>recommended to our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, yet where is the Man or Woman to be found, that lies under the lively impreſſions of theſe things: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall think it not impertinent, if I dwell upon that an Hour, which will be the ſubject of your Meditation, and Foundation of your comfort, if ever you underſtand what Chriſtianity in the life of it means. This only by the by, a little to quicken your attention. I come now to my buſineſs, to ſhew you wherein the Saints happineſs after death conſiſts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It conſiſts in a full everlaſting free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from evil, or any imperfection.</item>
               <item>2. It conſiſts in a compleat, perfect, and eternal enjoyment of all the good that our natures are capable of.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>It conſiſts in a full and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting freedom from evil, or any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection.</hi> And here I ſhall inſiſt upon ſome of thoſe evils and imperfections, which a Child of God ſhall be freed from, as ſoon as ever Death hath let the Soul out of the Body.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Saint is free from all ſin.</hi> The Bolts ſhall be knockt off, the Priſon walls broke down, and the poor Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94327:21"/>ſet at liberty. O bleſſed Jubilee! How glad would <hi>Paul</hi> have been, if when he cryed out in ſuch an agony: O wretched Man, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me? if he had heard a voice from Heaven ſaying, thy groans have pierced the Clouds, thy Prayer hath reached the Heavens, thy Petitions ſhall be granted immediately, would not this have been grateful news. When before a few days be at an end, this ſhall be the condition of every one of God's People. Now indeed if you liſſen to their Cloſets, you ſhould hear how dolefully they bemoan their condition, if you follow them into their Families, what is it that they would moſt deſire of God? is it not freedom from ſin? what complaints do they make of themſelves, that there ſhould be ſo great an unſutableneſs in them to God, that their hearts are unſenſible of the worth of divine things, that they ſhould have ſo little love to the Lord Chriſt, and be ſo little ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the kindneſs of the Redeemer; How weak and faint, how cold and dull in duty? how ready to betray their Lord, how cowardly in the cauſe of God? But death will for ever ſilence theſe complaints, death tares off <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s rags and preſents him before the Lord without ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing; ſin indeed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyeth the ungodly into another World, he reſts from his pleaſures, and his wicked works follow him: but it is far otherwiſe with the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſin was his burden, and Death ſhall unload <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im; ſin ſhall be confined to Hell, Heaven enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ains no ſuch deformity: This Tyrant ſhall no more inſlave any of Chriſt's ſubjects. The houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>David</hi> ſhall no longer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontend, that bloody conflict between the fleſh
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94327:22"/>and ſpirit ſhall then be determined by a final Victory, then the Soul will ſay, farewell my hard heart, farewell unbelief, farewell ingratitude; then thou ſhalt never entertain an unkind thought of God more; the lame and the blinde, and the <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buſites</hi> ſhall be ſmitten when King <hi>David</hi> comes to make his Palace in <hi>Zion,</hi> thy ſins muſt dye when the Lord cometh to take the full poſſeſſion of this Fort: Royal confeſſion of ſin ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be needleſs; no darkneſs ſhall cloud the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, no perverſneſs the will, no diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlineſs in the affections, no treachery in the memory; the Eyes ſhall be better employed than in beholding of vanity, the Eares ſhall not be locked againſt truth, the Hands far from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the Tongue from deceit, and the Feet from walking in ways of wickedneſs. And ſeems this a light matter to you who have gone bowed all your dayes under the preſſure of ſin; is it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to you to have all your iniquities done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as a Cloud, and your tranſgreſſions as a thick Cloud? Thus ſee what a kindneſs that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable enemy doth to all the ſubjects of Chriſt's Kingdom; what prayers, teares, and groans did gradually, it doth at one blow. Thus the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is delivered, the mourner made to rejoyce, and the great make-bate between God and the Soul, for ever diſcarded, and turned out of Doors. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 44.22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When a Chriſtian ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, he ſhall be freed from all the temptations of Sathan.</hi> Death ſets the Soul out of the Devils reach; this Angel hath nothing to do in Heaven, this Serpent ſhall not come into the higher Paradiſe, nor Sathan creep into this <hi>Eden:</hi> Now indeed he goes up
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94327:22"/>and down like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour, novv he ſets his Ginnes every vvhere to catch the unvvary Chriſtian: he uſeth his ſtratagems to ſurprize them, but then this adverſary ſhall be trod under Foot, his Fiery Darts ſhall be quenched, and his deſignes broken. O happy Day, vvhen will it come! vvhen the Devil ſhall be as unlikely to tempt, as our hearts to cloſe: vvhen vve are got once ſafe to reſt, the Devil ſhall as eaſily ſhake God's Throne, as our happineſs. Death turns the Key, Bolts and Bars this Enemy out; then, O then thou ſhalt ſee this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> caſt dead on the ſhore, and for ever diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled from making any reſiſtance againſt thee, or in the leaſt diſturbing thy peace. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The bleſſedneſs of the People of God conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in their being freed from the frownes and flatteries of the World.</hi> In life time thou art fain to fight thy way to peace, to diſpute every ſtep thou goeſt, and canſt never have a quiet Hour vvhile thou haſt ſuch ill Neighbours: There is an old quarrel between the Seed of the Woman, and the Serpent, and the enmity is radicated, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end can be cooled with nothing but Death. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, expect not as long as any of that <hi>Cainiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Generation breath, that thou ſhouldeſt be long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cure, In the World you ſhall have tribulation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut be of good cheer, Chriſt hath overcome the World, Joh. 16.33. What though they ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eat words, Priſon, Halters, Faggot? Thou ſhalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e long ride in ſtate to glory, and then let them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their worſt: When thou art in Heaven, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay curſe and increaſe their own miſery, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey ſhall not in the leaſt diminiſh thy tranquillity. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d as for their flatteries, they ſhall ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94327:23"/>thing, the beauty of this inſeriour World will be darkned by the brightneſs of that Light which Death leads thee into; its excellencies will be quite eclipſed, its allurements will loſe their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Who can chooſe but contemn the Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that knows what Heaven meaneth? O how low an eſteem have the moſt experienced Men here o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the World! Honours and riches are accounted very inconſiderable things to them which under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the difference between finite and infinite the diſproportion between time and Eternity Death bloweth the duſt out of our eyes, it pluck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off the Vail, and ſhews one quickly the glory o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both Worlds: and ſo it is not leſt long to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, which is to be preferred, droſs or ſilver braſs or gold, a dunghil or a Palace: there wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be no thought of returning to <hi>Egypt</hi> or <hi>Goſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> either in them which know the fruitfulneſs of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpiritual <hi>Canaan,</hi> the accommodations of the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the pleaſure of the holy Court.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>At Death he ſhall reſt from all his pains there is no fear of ſickneſs, ſorrowes, and ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> The Stone, Gout, and Plague are Diſtempers th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> none labour with there: that Aire is clear, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſin which infecteth other places, never got foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there; they that ſcarce know what a Day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eaſe now means ſhall then forget their ſorrow their conſtitutions ſhall be mended, their craz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bodies, that needed to be propped up by A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have now no need of ſuch helps: the lame ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leap, the blinde ſee, the weak ſhall be ſtrong, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> crooked ſtrait, they which were in deaths oft ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be never in danger. O happy alteration! th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grave will refine and alter our Bodies, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall there bury all imperfections, and this mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:94327:23"/>ſhall put on immortality, and this corruptible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption. There the weary ſhall be at reſt. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.18. <hi>Job</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The bleſsedneſs of the deceaſed Saints conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h in their perfect freedome from all wants, and fear of want.</hi> Here they have their daily want, and in the ſweat of their brows they muſt eat their Bread. The World in its beſt eſtate is made up of vanities and troubles. How much need have we of the help of our fellow-creatures? we can't live without the uſe of their bodies and lives: we want their ſervice to till our Grounds, and to carry our weak Bodyes, that can ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſcarce go under their own burden. What ſhift could we make, if the influences of the Sun Moon and Stars were ſuſpended? what lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table complaint ſhould we make, if God ſhould ſeal up the Fountains of Water? how ſoon ſhould we faint, if he ſhould make the Heavens as Iron, and the Earth as braſs? What Element can we want, what Creature could we well ſpare? But the time is coming, that Day will ſhortly begin, whoſe brightneſs will make the Sun dark, and the Moon to diſappear, and all the Stars to leave their Spheres as uſeleſs. O unbelief, how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably doſt thou rob us of the comforts, which the very fore-thoughts of that hour might bring in! Dwell O my trembling Soul upon the Meditation of theſe things. Is there no truth nor weight in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe Scriptures? <hi>Eſ.</hi> 60.19. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 21.29. Give in thy Anſwer. <hi>Why then art thou caſt down O my ſoul, and why art thou diſquieted within me?</hi> Wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, and be of good courage, wait I ſay upon the Lord.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>This happy Man ſhall be quite freed of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94327:24"/>whatſoever may argue an imperfect state.</hi> Some of thoſe very graces that are now ſo uſeful and neceſſary, when their work is done, ſhall be laid aſide as uſeleſs, I mean Faith, Hope, Patience, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; all which ſpeak ſomething of imperfection, ſhall then be ſwallowed up of love. They now help to lead the Soul out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> conduct tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the red Sea, and Wilderneſs, and ſend Spices into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and bring good tidings out of that Land, they ſee <hi>Sihon, Og,</hi> and <hi>Amaleck</hi> diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted, and their Power broken, they go to the Borders of the promiſed Land: nay, they get up to <hi>Piſga,</hi> and upon Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> there they bid the Soul farewell. Faith, like a skilful Pilot, keeps cloſe to the Ship, till it ſee it out of danger. Faith, like loyal <hi>Barzillai,</hi> brings in abundant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for the Soul, in all its ſtreights, and comes with it to the banks of <hi>Jordan,</hi> to the brink o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eternity; but there, there it takes its final leave, and ſends over young <hi>Chimham</hi> to wait upon the King at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it ſends love over into Heaven t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dwell there with the Lord for ever. O bleſſed ſtate, when faith ſhall be ſwallowed up of ſight. Here we live by faith, and not by ſenſe or ſight in glory we ſhall live by ſenſe and ſight, and not by faith. The ſhaddow ſhall vaniſh when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is come; hope, patience, deſire, and fear ſhall all paſs away, and be ſwallowed up with an eternal fruition, poſſeſſion, and ſecurity. Happy are the People that are in ſuch a caſe, their clouds are quite blown over, they need neither Wind or Sails, now they are ſafe landed. What think you now of a Child of God, is it worth the while to be religious, is holineſs a folly now? and yet this is not all, come a little further, and I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94327:24"/>will ſhew you greater things ſtill. All this is bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the privative part of their happineſs. I come now to touch a little upon the poſitive part; but what an Ocean am I now lanching into, who can tell all the priviledges of a Citizen of <hi>Zion,</hi> what Pen can deſcribe the honour and dignities of the Sons of God? But that I may heighten your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and a little antedate your comforts, I ſhall in the next place ſhew ſomething of the poſitive part.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The bleſſedneſs of thoſe which dye in the Lord, conſiſts poſitively,</p>
            <p>Firſt in this, that they ſhall enter into the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the Angels, they ſhall leave any longer converſing with mortals, and, inſtead of weeping friends, ſee themſelves compaſſed with ſinging Angels. How do you think that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was affected, who inſtead of Beggars, Crippels, and Dogs, had a Guard of Angels waiting upon him? What an extaſy of joy was he ſurprized vvith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. This honour have all the Saints. We think the ſight of a King, the look of a Prince, the company of a Lord a great matter: what are they, it compared with the leaſt of the Captains of the Lord's Hoſt? How vaſt is the difference between Fleſh and Spirit? and yet this favour the Lord is pleaſed to confer upon the leaſt of his Children. And how glad are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels themſelves of the ſociety of the pooreſt Saint? they are glad even here to be doing offices of love for them, many a danger they delivered them from, many a mercy they conveyed from their Father to them; but theſe earthly Bodyes were ſcarce capable of communications with ſuch noble and ſpiritual Creatures, but at Death they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94327:25"/>ſhall know their old friends and fellow-ſervants, and bleſs God with them, and for them for ever. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. And theſe Chariots and Horſemen of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall carry up <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his Fathers Houſe, and there the Sons of God ſhall ſhout for joy. Time was, the ſight of an Angel would make a Saint tremble, but then it ſhall make them to Triumph: and what ſtories will they tell them, of the providences of God toward them, and joyn with them in the high praiſes of his goodneſs and love? But all this is but little to what follows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At Death, the ſouls of believers are made perfect in holineſs. How will they in a moment ſee themſelves as white as Snow? how glorious ſhall the Kings Daughter be, when her beauty is perfect, how lovelily will ſhe look, when ſhe's clad with innocent purity, how excellent when her royal Husband the Lord Chriſt ſhall be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely taken with her? Will he not then ſay, thou art all fair my love, there is no ſpot in thee. Come with me from <hi>Lebanon</hi> my Spouſe, with me from <hi>Lebanon,</hi> from the top of <hi>Amana,</hi> from the top of <hi>Shenir</hi> and <hi>Hermon,</hi> from the Lyons Dens, from the Mountains of Leopards. Thou haſt raviſhed my heart, my Siſter, my Spouſe, thou with one Chain of thy Neck: How fair is thy love, my Siſter, my Spouſe? <hi>&amp;c. Cant.</hi> 4.7, 8, 9, 10. If the Lord ſee ſo much beauty here in his Church, what will he do hereafter, when he ſhall have waſh'd away all her defilements, and taken out her ſtains, and have decked her with his Jewels, and put on her Wedding Garment? That Day is coming, O my ſoul! when will the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94327:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhaddows flee away, when will Days and Nights be all at an end, when will time be ſpent, when ſhall the Curtain be drawn? O that, that's the place! thou ſhalt then love that precious Jeſus, with a Seraphick and Angel-like love, thou wilt then as much delight and rejoyce in him, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, David,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> did. Thy drowſie Soul ſhall be as nimble and active in the ſervice of thy great Maker, as <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias;</hi> thou ſhalt praiſe him Day and Night, and be no more weary than the Angels themſelves: thou ſhalt perfectly underſtand the vvill of God, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obey it: thou ſhalt be holy as God is holy. And what vvould you now give for ſuch a frame? hovv glad vvould you be to feel a connaturality to divine imployments, hovv happy vvould you think your ſelves, if your heart vvere alvvayes as God vvould have it? Is it not for this, that you faſt and pray? Is it not for this, that you hear, read, and meditate? Is not this the end of Sacraments? Well, be of good cheer, in Mount <hi>Zion</hi> there ſhall be deliverance and holineſs: <hi>Obed.</hi> 17. And is all this nothing, ſeemeth it ſtill a ſmall priviledge to be a Child of God, and like our Father? vvho that underſtands this vvould not bid Death vvelcome, and ſay novv Grave do thy vvorſt? Ask <hi>Paul,</hi> and he vvill tell you, that upon this account he groans: enquire of <hi>David,</hi> and he vvill let you underſtand, that he never expects ſatisfaction, till he avvake vvith God's likeneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another thing vvherein the bleſſedneſs of a Chriſtian at Death lyes, is this, the ſight of Chriſt. What can be more deſired by a Child of God, than to behold and enjoy him, by vvhom
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94327:26"/>all the mercies we have, and all that we expect, ſlow in to us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. That good old Saint, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.30. thought it a Heaven upon Earth to ſee him, though his Majeſty was vailed, and the brightneſs of his glory wrapped up, and covered by his humanity, he doth ſing a Requiem to his Soul, and ſay, <hi>Now let thy Servant depart in peace, for mine Eyes have ſeen thy Salvation.</hi> How were <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> affected at his transfiguration, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17 2. What an admirable frame doth the Spouſe ſeem to be in, when ſhe ſaw only the ſhadow and back-parts of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved one, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.16. She can't tell when to have done commending of him. But all this is but a ſmall thing, compared to the ſight which they ſhall ſee, when their graces ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, and their Soul like him; and then ſhall they behold the King in his beauty; no longer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorn of the World, no longer in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and want, no longer crucified and rejected; but Jeſus, the expreſs Image of his Father, and the brightneſs of his glory, accompanyed with Millions of Angels, all at his command, and yet for all this, caſting a gracious Eye upon them; then ſhall the Soul behold him face to face, who did, and ſuffered ſuch wonderful things for it; 'twas he that came out of his Fathers boſome, 'twas he that ſtept out of his Throne, and put off his Robes, that came leaping over the Mountains, and skipping over the Hills, running thorow a thouſand difficulties, that he might pluck thee out of thy miſery, and deliver thee out of the paw of the Lyon, and the Bear, that he might redeem thee from the power of Sin, Death, and Hell. How will the Heavens eccho with Songs of joy,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94327:26"/>when the Bride, the Lamb's Wife, ſhall come to dwell with her Husband for ever? <hi>Iſay</hi> 33.17. Chriſt is the deſire of Nations, the joy of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the delight of the Father, and he in whom he is well pleaſed. What ſolace then muſt that Soul be filled with, that hath the poſſeſſion of him to all Eternity; Is not his love better than wine, and a look of his countenance to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Corn and Oyl? Is not his kindneſs to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued above life it ſelf? What meaneſt thou then O my Soul, that thou doſt ſo dread his coming? Why art thou ſo loath to be with him? Why art thou afraid of the enjoyment of him? Will thy Redeemer make thee a ſlave, hath Heaven chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Nature, and made him leſs deſirable? Will thy Saviour make thee miſerable? Awake then, O ye Saints, and ſtand a tip-toe, wait, watch, and long till thou ſee him, who alone can fill thy Soul! fight, ſtrive, and run, till you enjoy. One ſmile of his, one look of his love, is worth the pleaſures of ten Worlds: where is thy heart, where are thy deſires, what's become of thy love? if Chriſt doth not affect, draw, and fire thee, what will? but when thou ſhalt ſee Chriſt indeed, his very looks will ſo warm thy Soul, that thou ſhalt in a moment feel a divine flame, which ſhall never be extinguiſhed, as long as Chriſt, the object of thy love, ſhall live: the ſight of Chriſt will put new life into thy Soul, and make thy love and joy freſh for ever; this is he, O my Soul, that was wounded, that thou mighteſt be healed; this is he who was Crowned vvith Thorns, that thou mighteſt be Crovvned vvith Glory; this, this is he that dyed, that thou mighteſt live. Is not all the Glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94327:27"/>vvrapped up in him? Are not the Treaſures of divine kindneſs, which vvere ſometimes hid in him, novv opened? Tell me now, O my ſoul, is there any in tvvo Worlds comparable to him? Was not that he that ſheltered thee from the ſtorms of God's vvrath? Was not that precious Body, the Shield vvhich blunted the Svvord of Juſtice, and kept the Arrovves of the Almighty from doing dreadful execution upon thee, an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, Traytor, and Rebel? Was it not he that laid dovvn the price, that bought thy pardon, that purchaſed this Inheritance? vvas it not he that fed thee vvith his Body, that broached his heart blood, to quench the thirſt of thy Soul, the luſts of thy heart, and the flames of God's indignation? Look upon him, is he not made up of love? I ſee now, it is not for nothing, that the Virgins did love him, it was not vvithout good reaſon, that the Spouſe vvas ſick; it vvas not vvithout very good cauſe, that the Saints did ſo long to be vvith him; to be with him did I ſay? vvho that hears of him, can chooſe but vviſh to ſee him, vvho that ſees him, can live without him, who that lives vvith him can leave him? What mean the World? Sure they are dead, blind, or mad: but vvhere am I now? This is a ſubject ſo ſvveet, that I can't tell hovv to make an end, O that I might ſee, knovv, and enjoy! look dear Jeſus upon me, and let me go, and tell the World thy beauties, let me every day have a little ſight of thee, that I may commend thee a thouſand times more feelingly, and that I may command the affections of all that hear of thee, that nothing but thy love may ſerve their turns. Pardon me, that this admirable one hath
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94327:27"/>dravvn out my thoughts ſo largely. If you can but love after all this, and ſee him when you dye with comfort, you will ſay, I were too ſhort in his praiſes, and too ſuperficial in his commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that the half was not told you.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The bleſſedneſs of departed Saints lies in this, that they ſhall meet with all the Children of God, and have communion with the ſpirits of the juſt, made perfect. Thou ſhalt then meet thy beſt friends, whoſe company was ſo warming, whoſe words were ſo incouraging, whoſe lives did ſo much command Religion, their Faces did then ſhine, their converſation was in Heaven: but O what an alteration is there in them for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter! their Souls are now like Chriſt, nothing but grace, love, and praiſe: no difference in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no pride or paſſion, nothing that offends. And how vvill they vvelcome you to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe, you that took ſweet counſel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that went to the Houſe of God, that talk'd of that glory, how glad will you be, when you meet in it? Nay, Death will bring you acquainted with all theſe famous Worthies, of whom the World was not worthy, the noble Champions of Chriſt, which thought not their lives dear to them, ſo they might but finiſh their courſe with joy: this Porter opens the Door, and lets the Saints Soul into that Palace, where all the Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of that great Prince reſide; and thou ſhalt ſtand alſo with them upon Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> in the preſence of that Mighty King, and ſhalt behold, and live in his glory for ever: And is all this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable? What would I give to ſee <hi>Enoch,</hi> that walked with God? How glad ſhould I be to be acquainted with <hi>Elias?</hi> how joyful, if I might
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94327:28"/>have ſome diſcourſe with <hi>Paul?</hi> Would it not make one couragious in the cauſe of God, if one could hear <hi>Daniel,</hi> or the Three Children tell the ſtory of their deliverance? How ſhould one be pleaſed to have it from the Mouth of <hi>Moſes, Joſhuah,</hi> and <hi>Caleb.</hi> what God did for <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Fields of <hi>Ham,</hi> the Red-Sea, and the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? and how he brought them into the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> hovv do you think you ſhould be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected at ſuch things as theſe? vvhy? as formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable as Death looks, it's he that brings us to the ſpeech of all theſe. How loath are we novv to part, when a knot of us have got together, to talk about the things of another World? are not the Saints the excellent ones, in whom is our delight? is not the empty diſcourſe of the unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced World tedious, and their Company a burden? Why? Heaven hath in it none but Saints, and Angels, and the bleſſed God. Is not that Company indeed? and all their work will be to admire, praiſe, and love God, and to take infinite delight, and complacency in him to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. O what acclamations of joy vvill there be, vvhen all the Children of God ſhall meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, vvithout fear of being diſturbed by the Antichriſtian and <hi>Cainiſh</hi> brood! when they meet, and never part, but joyn in Hallelujahs for ever. That, that's the melody, vvhen a Quire of ten thouſand times ten thouſand of Angels ſhall ſing an Eternal Song, and the hundred and forty and four thouſand, and that innumerable Company, out of all Nations, Tongues, and Kindreds, ſhall anſvver, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſing, honour, glory, and power, be unto Him that ſits upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi> Rev. 5.13. Luk.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94327:28"/>13.28, 29. Heb. 11.22. Eph. 2.19.</p>
            <p n="5">5. An other thing, wherein the bleſſedneſs of the Saints departed conſiſts, is, that then all their Prayers ſhall be ſully anſwered, their deſires ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and hopes enjoyed. They now oft, with ſorrow, hear the reproaches of the wicked, who are ready to ask them, vvhere is their God? vvhat is become of their ſaſts, tears, and groans, to vvhat purpoſe do they afflict themſelves? what profit is it for them to call upon God? what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is there in ſerving the Almighty? The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed boaſt of their hearts deſire, and are ready to ſleight Religion, as a uſeleſs and contemptible thing. But is there not a time a coming, vvhen the godly may ask them, vvhat profit they have novv in their pleaſures, vvhat comfort in their greatneſs, what fruit of all their labours? and with unſpeakable ſatisfaction, produce their Crown, and ſay, This, this was the prize that we contended for; this was the reward that vve had in our Eye, this was the glory and honour which we ſo highly valued; <hi>This is our God in whom we have truſted,</hi> Eſ. 25.9. The Saints ſhall then ſee, that it was not in vain to ſeek, knock, and wait; then they ſhall underſtand, that nothing was loſt, which was ſpent for their Souls and Heaven: they ſhall ſhortly know, that the pooreſt hearty groan was heard, the quickeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations were not unobſerved, and that the vveakeſt ſincere Prayers were able to pierce the Heavens. O who would not ſerve ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who can't forget any of his! nay, the Lord will infinitely out-do their requeſts, and give them more than their Tongue; could ask, and mindes conceive. This is the portion of them that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94327:29"/>ſeek thee, that ſeek thy face, O <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. At Death, the Believer ſhall be poſſeſſed of God, and know what the beatifical Viſion means: and if you would be better ſatisfied what this is, my requeſt is, that you would live holily, and go, and ſee. And if after a ſight and ſenſe of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible glory, you finde that I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived you, by making you to over-value it, I am contented to bear the blame of an Impoſtor. I am here but brief, becauſe I muſt confeſs my Meditations are now at a loſs, and ſilence, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment muſt ſpeak the reſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That which is no ſmall addition to a Saints happineſs is this, that there is no fear of loſing of it; his Enemies can't rob him, for they are all ſafe enough, and his Treaſure is locked up there, where neither Moth, nor Ruſt can corrupt, nor Thieves break thorow, and ſteal; the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may then rejoyce over his Enemy, and ſay, vvho ſhall ſeparate me from the love of God? they that are ſafe in Heaven, need not to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any fears of loſing their Inheritance. If God that made Heaven, and brought them to it, can ſecure them, if Chriſt that bought it for them, can make good his purchaſe, if all challenges are laid aſide, they are vvell enough; thy houſe ſhall not be ſhaken, thy comforts are durable, and the leaſe of thy Inheritance runs parallel with the life of God, and muſt not expire till Eternity be ſpent. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>If.</hi> 54 10. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 35. <hi>laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. The laſt thing that I ſhall mention, wherein the happineſs of the Dead, that dye in the Lord, conſiſts, is in the full and joyful aſſurance of a glorious Reſurrection, and acquaittance at the day
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94327:29"/>of Judgment. Their Bodies are the ſacred Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples wherein God did dwell, they are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be buried in forgetfulneſs, but ſhall be reſerved as Jewels in a Cabinet, and at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, they ſhall be furbuſhed, and ſet in Glory; the very Duſt of the Saints is precious, and thoſe very Members, that were aſſiſtant to the Soul, in the Worſhip of God, ſhall partake of its Glory; and upon this account, the People of God dye in faith, that their Bodies and Souls ſhall have a bleſſed Meeting; upon this account, believers weep not at the Interment of their Chriſtian brethren, as thoſe which have no hope, but the thoughts of a future meeting ſwallows up the grief of preſent parting; they underſtand that it would be a piece of unkindneſs to be grieved at their happineſs, and that it ſpeaks too much ſelf-love, and too great a disbelief of their unſeen glory, and too much deſire, that our wills ſhould be done before God's. What a deal of ſorrow would the ſound belief of the reality of inviſibles prevent? With what chearfulneſs might the dear Children of God part, when they think how certainly, and ſpeedily they ſhall ſee one another again, never to part more. If the Doctrine of the Reſurrection were but better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, if the Grave were but looked upon, as a Chamber to reſt in, and if faith could but take Death to be but an undreſſing, to put on better Raiment, how contentedly then ſhould we be unclothed, that we might be clothed with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: And why ſeems it a thing incredible, that the Body ſhould riſe again? Is it a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, that he which made a World out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94327:30"/>ſhould raiſe up our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>feleſs Duſt, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Bones? Is any thing too hard for the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty? Was he put to it, when he made Man out of a lump o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Clay? Is it beyond his power to raiſe Children to <hi>Abraham</hi> out of the very Stones? Can nothing be acted by an Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Agent, but it muſt firſt be forged in our brains? Shall God indeed come and bow to us, and wiſdome ask counſel of folly, how he ſhould manage his affairs? Doth not God every Day do as great wonders, as this? and hath not he given our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith very conſiderable helps in this matter? Doth not his Yearly providences preach the truth of this Doctrine? What Farmer thinks his Seed loſt, when it's buried under the Clods, when the Winter hath diſrobed the Medowes, and covered them with a white Mantle, will you therefore conclude they ſhall never be dreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with their Greens, and decked with their Flowers? but it all this ſignify nothing, what do you think of what God hath done already? was <hi>Lazarus</hi> his Reſurrection a cheat? and were the Evangeliſts miſtaken, which tell us of the riſing of many of the Saints, and that they went into the holy City? Is Chriſt ſtill in the Grave? and if theſe things be otherwiſe, why ſhould not that which hath been, be again: What? hath God let power than he bad: Is his Arm weaker than it was? Is the Grave too ſtrong for him? And are the Doors of it ſo faſt locked, that his Key can't open them? Did Chriſt promiſe more than he could make good, when he ſaid, <hi>I will raiſe them up at the laſt Day.</hi> O unbelief! how doſt thou ſpoyl my comforts, and daunt my courage,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94327:30"/>truth can't lye, the Almighty can't be weak, God is ſtill like himſelf. And if the caſe be ſo, what a good condition is the dead Saint in? his life is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd with Chriſt, and when Chriſt, who is his life, ſhall appear, he alſo ſhall appear with him in Glory; And what kind of Body will this be? when it ſhall be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the glorious Body of Chriſt; perfect, active, unmortal. Look up to the Sky, do you ſee how bright that Body is, which light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, the whole World, how haſtily that Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion runs to finiſh his appointed courſe? vvhy that cold and dead Body ſhall ere long be as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, as the Sun in its ſtrength, and as lively in its motions? How caſtly will it mount into the Aire to meet the Lord in the Clouds? how actively will it paſs from one ſide of the Heavens to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with as much expedition, as it ſhall deſire? how readily will it run at the command of its great Maſter, and keep pace with thoſe winged Meſſengers the Angels, they ſhall be no longer ſuch heavy, dull pieces of Clay, and bundles of Diſeaſes, but when they are called out of their Bed, they ſhall be refreſhed abundantly, and with joy meet their Souls, and be acted by them. O methinks what kind of greeting will theſe two old Companions have, when they ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in an other World; what ſtrange ſalutations will they give each other. Will not the Soul ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Body, where hadſt thou, O my friend, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat glorious ſplendor? who clothed thee in ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovely a dreſs? how cameſt thou by that Majeſty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd beauty? Art thou that Body which wert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ont to bear me company to the Houſe of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re thoſe the Eyes that wept ſo oft? Are thoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94327:31"/>the Feet which travelled ſo many miles to hear the World. O excellent alteration! well, now you ſee that your pains was not altogether loſt, and as for me, I have beheld the glory of our royal Bridegroom, I have viewed his Chambers, and have lodged in his boſom, ever ſince you and I parted, and I have found that he hath made good all his promiſes to a tittle. I had no ſooner parted from thee, but he ſent his Angels for me, and they brought me with joy into his Pavilian, and there did I ſee him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with millions of ſuch Courtiers, and all our old friends I ſaw there; and O ſuch joy, happineſs, and pleaſure is unſpeakable; but what ſound is that which I hear, Is it not the Voice of the Arch Angel? we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded away; Who is that, do you think that rides in ſuch ſtate, with ſo great a Train after him? who ſits upon that Throne; hark, hark, he calls you, make haſte, make haſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.— <hi>Come you bleſſed of my Father enter now into your Maſters joy:</hi> Dwell in the Manſions that I have prepared, poſſeſs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Inheritance that I have given you: You ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mine, and I am yours, I have betrothed you to my ſelf long ſince, and now the marriag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Day is come, and I take you to be my Spou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for ever. Before my Father, and theſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Servants, I take you to be my wedded Wif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ever: and I do now for ever acquit you from all offences, they ſhall never be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred any more; I inveſt you with the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory that I poſſeſs, I indow you with all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Riches of my Kingdome, I will remove what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94327:31"/>may offend you; look how your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies tremble, I have already vindicated you from all thoſe falſe imputations, which their malice did caſt upon you, I have ſilenced your accuſers, and for ever ſtopped the Mouths of their great adverſaries, and they ſhall imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately be removed out of their ſight, and pay dearly for all their abuſes. Juſtice, call thoſe Priſoners to the Bar.— <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> And now my beloved, the Cloud is quite gone; come now into my Armes, I will never frown more, come away my love, my Dove, my undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and rejoyce in my love, you and I will never part more; what I have is yours, I am well pleaſed in my choice, my Father loves you, as I do; you ſhall be where I am, and have the ſame pleaſures that I have, and live as I do to Eternity. <hi>Amen, hallelujah, even ſo come Lord Jeſus, come quickly. Mat.</hi> 26.81, <hi>&amp;c. John</hi> 17.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33, 54. <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>Mal.</hi> 8.16, 17 <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. And is not this a ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for thoſe poor ſervices, which the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever doth perform, while he lives upon the Earth? Is there nothing in all this? Seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to you a ſmall matter to be free from ſin? Is it no favour to be ſecured from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han? Is not that a deſirable place, vvherein there is ſo much glory, that the World in its beſt dreſs, looks like a deform'd ugly thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o it? Who would not be glad to have all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94327:32"/>Diſeaſes cured, pains removed, and wants ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied? Will not that be a Day of comfort indeed? when Faith ſhall be ended in ſight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hope in enjoyment, deſire in a delightful and Eternal fruition? vvhen patience ſhall have done all its work, when an everlaſting Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee ſhall put a period to all ſorrows? Is it no honour to be conveyed into Heaven by a Guard of Angels? Do you count it an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable favour to ſee King <hi>Jeſus</hi> in his Throne? Have you no deſire to be with all your good friends, and to know all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites of Heaven? Would you not reckon it a great mercy, to have all your Prayers anſwered to the full? Will there be no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the beatifical Viſion? Would not all this be the more conſiderable, if it might laſt alwayes? Is it no ſatisfaction to you, to know that your Body ſhall be raiſed, like Chriſt's Body? and that your Body and Soul ſhall be publickly acquitted, owned, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before the great Court: and after this, live in the ſame glory that Chriſt lives in: If all this be worth the having, then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Saint is no loſer, and we may well ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead which dye in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewed who are they which dye in the Lord; and proved that ſuch are bleſſed, and ſhewed where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their bleſſedneſs doth conſiſt. I now come to make ſome Improvement of this Doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:94327:32"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">USE </seg>I</label> Firſt, by way of Information; that holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is no ſuch ſilly thing, as the World thinks it to be: Sure, if there be any thing in reſt, happineſs, and glory, then the Saint ſcarce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the imputation of Fanaticiſme: They which have received their Wages, vvill ſay, that the ſervice of God is not unprofitable, and they finde themſelves to be no looſers, though credit, eſtate, and blood were ſpent in the cauſe of Chriſt: Should you ask them, who, thorow may Tribulations, have entred into the Kingdom of Heaven? Whether they repent of their diligence for Heaven, whether God hath not paid them double for their ſelf-denyal, loſſes, and kindneſſes? VVould they not cry out truly, God is good to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> how great is that Treaſure, that is laid up for them that fear him? Never let any grutch to ſerve God cheerfully, for verily he is a rewarder of them which diligently ſeek him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">USE </seg>II</label> If the Saint be ſo happy in another World, then let us all examine, whether we are in the number of thoſe Perſons, for whom ſuch things are prepared. Conſider ſirs, that this is not like to be every Mans portion, all Men and Women are not Kings and Queens, nor all the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> Heirs of ſuch an Inheritance;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94327:33"/>few run ſo as to obtain, few fight ſo as to conquer, and get the Field, few act, as if this bleſſedneſs were worth the minding; and let me tell you, Heaven is not got with a vvet Finger, moſt do their work by the halves, and though the Spirit move them, the Word, providence, call them, the Miniſters beſeech them, yet all will not do; they will not be perſwaded, but a few lazy wiſhes will do, as well as all the ſeriouſneſs in the World, and thus they will put things to the venture, and count a hazard, in the matters of their Souls and Eternity, but a trivial thing: VVe can't for our lives get Men to be in good earneſt, but they will bleſs themſelves, though God curſe them; and take it for granted, that all is well, when God knows they are in as ſad a condition, as can well be imagined on this ſide of Damnation. We tell them that moſt miſtake, and that miſtake here is the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable; and yet ſtill Men are aſleep; and what if this ſhould be thy condition, O Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that comeſt hither for faſhion ſake, and ſits there very trim and cheary? VVhat ſayſt thou Man, art provided for Eternity? What title haſt thou to glory? Doſt thou knovv what it means to be convinced of ſin? Was it ever made loathſome to thee? And canſt thou ſay thou hateſt it with a perfect hatred? and that not only as contrary to thee, and as it brings Hell, Miſery, and Damnation with it, but as it is contrary to God, abuſing his goodneſs, hating his purity, dethroning his Majeſty; hath ſin ever looked you in the face
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94327:33"/>beſmeered with the blood of Chriſt? Were you ever made to underſtand your abſolute need of Chriſt? Did you ever make a compleat reſignation of your ſelf to him? and hath it been your bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to act for him? and have you felt any ſtrength coming from him, enabling of you to bring forth fruit meet for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and to dye unto ſin, and to live unto righteouſneſs? and yet after all this, have you looked upon your ſelf as an unprofitable ſervant? what expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience have you in theſe things? put this queſtion home to thy conſcience; ſay, am I acquainted with ſuch things or no? are theſe things Riddles to me, or do I know what they mean? well now, have you done as I bid you, and what ſaith conſcience? is it altogether ſilent, or doth it put you off till another time? why, then ſpeak again, and again, and ask it whether this be not a ſerious queſtion, and a buſineſs of ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: but becauſe People for the moſt part trifle in this great buſineſs, I ſhall ſpeak ſomething by way of Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conviction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">USE </seg>III</label> It is ſo, that they are bleſſed that dye
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94327:34"/>in the Lord, then what a caſe are they in, which live and dye out of Chriſt? if none but the friends and Children of God be thus happy, what will become of them which are aliens from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that live without God in the World? Where ſhall the wicked and ungodly appear? O what a lamentable condition are moſt of the World in! if we could ſee all the dead Souls in this Congregation, what a ghaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſight would it be, ſhould God ſtrike all them dead, which lye in their ſins, and know not Chriſt; it is to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Aſſembly would be far thinner than it is? ſhould the Graves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the Souls and Bones ſay to us, make haſt, make haſt, up get your Souls dreſſed, for within three Days you muſt lye in this black and cold Chamber with us? How would this make moſt of our Faces to gather paleneſs, and our joynts ready to knock one againſt another? but what if another Voice ſhould ſecond it, and one ſhould come roaring out of Hell, wrapped about with Flames, and ſhould ſay, it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God, they that dye in ſin muſt be buried in Hell,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94327:34"/>and if this very moment, you do not turn, you muſt take a place with us in thoſe torments, from which there is no redemption; Would this move you? why ſirs, is there not as much reaſon that you ſhould believe God, as the dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? O what wonders are ſtupid ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners! how unconcerned do they go up and down, as if it were a very eaſy thing to prepare for Death, and a needleſs thing to think of Eternity. O you that know a little, what the life and death of a Soul is, come help us to mourn over our dead, Doth not the very Aire ſmell of the dead? Are not their numbers ſcarce to be computed? whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Towns, Cities, and ſcarce one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul amongſt them! O where, where is our pity? how can we bear to ſee ſo many millions go to the Pit, and not beſtow one tear upon them? what's the matter, O my Soul, that thou art no more compaſſionate? would <hi>Heſter, Jeremiah, Paul;</hi> nay, would the King and Princes of <hi>Niniveh</hi> have been no more troubled, if Souls had been in the ſame danger in their Days, as they are in ours. But that I may a little move my ſelf and others; let me commune a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94327:35"/>little with you, you are yet in your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and have the uſe of your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and are not brutes nor ſtones; ſhall I have leave to reaſon the caſe a little with you? do you never uſe your reaſon? have you not a principle of ſelf-preſervation? do you never conſider whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you are going, while you make haſt to Hell? Do you never think of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? and is it ſo frightful a place, that you ſhould be afraid of it? will it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do you to be ſaved? and is that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, which I have ſet before you, ſo contemptible a thing, that you will not ſo much as give the thoughts of it one Hours entertainment in your Soul? Can you be contented without it, and prefer your ſhort lived pleaſures before it? if the caſe be ſo, thank your ſelves, if you have your choice, blame not God, if he deny you that which you thought not worth the accepting: As for us Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, we call God, Angels, and Men to witneſs, that we have told you of your danger, and if you will not take warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who can help it; if we knew what in the World to do to prevent your ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, God forbid but that we ſhould rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily do it, but if after all your threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94327:35"/>perſwaſions, and intreaties, you will go on ſtill, why, your blood be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your own Souls; but though I ſpeak thus, I hope better things of many here preſent, and things that do accompany ſalvation. I ſhall ſpeak for your incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in the next Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">USE </seg>IV</label> Is it ſo, that they are bleſſed that dye in the Lord, why then ſhould the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever be ſo much afraid of Death? What though it be the King of terrors, is it ſo to all? Have not ſome handled this Serpent without any fear? What have I been proving all this while? Is there not one word of ſenſe in all that hath been ſpoken? get but this ſecured that you are a Child of God, make but the King you friend, and then neither his Serjeant, nor his Porter will do you any hurt, except to arreſt your enemies, and to open the Gates of his Palace to you, and to admit you into his preſence be counted an injury: who would be afraid of everlaſting reſt, why ſhould any one be ſo loth to have his diſeaſes healed, why ſhould we be ſo unwilling to receive that which we ſeem with much earneſtneſs to ask? Will the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94327:36"/>chooſe always to live confined? will he fall in love with his Chains, or be angry with him that comes to knock off his ſhackles? Is the miſerable Captive afraid of his liberty? why do you hear, pray, and read? to what purpoſe do you ſtrive, watch, and hope: Is it all for that which you tremble to have; what report doth faith bring of an other World? Doth it tell you that it is a Land of Darkneſs and ſorrow, or that it is a place of joy, pleaſure and happineſs? and what ſtill loth to depart? is this World the more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the two, and are thy ſins and carnal Companions more lovely than Chriſt! If the caſe be ſo, then why doſt thou talk of believing? Is this your faith? the truth of it is, if this be thy caſe, thou haſt no great reaſon to be over deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of leaving this World, for I perceive thou haſt built thy Houſe here, and doſt not take Heaven for thy Reſt, but in caſe of abſolute neceſſity, thou thinkeſt it a more tolerable place than Hell and Torments. But thou art not the Perſon, that I have now to do with, I ſhall ſpeak a word or two to ſuch by and by: my errant it is to thee, O praying and believing Saint, I would fain hearten thee up a little, that thou may'ſt ſhew the World, that Heaven is not ſo ſorry a preferment, as that one ſhould hardly be perſwaded to accept of it, but that it is indeed what the Scriptures, Miniſters, and the Children of God ſay it is. O contradict not your profeſſion, and let the wicked ſee, that you have got ſomething in an other World, and that your happineſs begins there, where theirs ends. You work hard, and will you be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94327:36"/>afraid when Night comes to receive your wages, I hope you will not ſay that the Lord is a hard Maſter, and that his wages are not worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving. Let the wicked trouble, and the enemies of God fear, and let the workers of iniquity be afraid of their appearance before their Judge. But let not the faithful ſubject dread his King, the Wife her Husband, nor the Child his Father. I would ſain argue my ſelf and others out of thoſe ſlaviſh fears. Conſider ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, that now death hath loſt its ſting, and the Grave its bitterneſs, and a Saint (if he will but be as careful in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his watch, as he ought) may be able to ſpeak the ſame Language, as <hi>Paul</hi> did. <hi>O Death where is thy Sting, O Grave where is thy Victory?</hi> 1 Cor. 15 55. And to me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain; <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> If Death were like to make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration between Chriſt and thee, I ſhould then be far from blaming theſe thy fears, but I ſhould rather wonder, that they are not a thouſand times greater. But me-thinks a Soul that hath had many a ſweet kiſs from Chriſt, that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands what he is worth, and that hath ſome good reaſon to ſay, my beloved is mine, and I am his, me-thinks (I ſay) ſuch a one ſhould not deſire, that the Day of Marriage ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. Sure, were this but cleared, it were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to dye, but life it ſelf would be as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable an exerciſe of patience, as any thing in the World; let me therefore again expoſtulate the caſe with thee, and do what I can to ſhake off thoſe unwarrantable fears. What is it that you are ſo much afraid of? Is it of pains? why, when you are dead, you will feel none, they be the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94327:37"/>which feel pains, and I believe there are few living, but at one time or other feel as much pain as ſome do in their death; and if their pains be acute, they are like to be ſhort, and if they be not acute, they may be the more eaſily born. Are you loath to leave your friends, I hope God's Saints, and Angels are other gueſs friends than any you have here. You have a fine Houſe, and ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, alas, 'tis but a Hog-ſty, or a Dunghil, if compared with Heaven. But how ſhall I do for my Children? what will become of them, when I am dead and gone? Why, do you make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of God's promiſe? Is not he a Father to the Fatherleſs? And is it not his command, that we ſhould leave our Fatherleſs Children with him? Can't God take as good care of them as you? O, but the Grave is a doleful place, and who can think with any comfort of being nail'd up in a Coffin, and covered over with Earth, and of rotting under ground; Why Man, is the Reſurrection no comfort to thee? if there were no ſuch thing, this arguing were the more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable; who are you I pray, that you ſhould be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged above all the Kings and Monarcks ſince the beginning of the World, which of them have ſecured themſelves from the power of Death? which of them could retain their breath a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when Death had received his Commiſſion to ſtop it. Are you better than <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> did not <hi>David</hi> ſee corruption, and the Fathers, where are they? nay, did not Chriſt dye, and dye ſo bitter a death, as I believe never any from the foundation of the World ever did. Muſt God make thee the third that muſt be ſingled out from Man-kind, to be tranſlated to Glory?
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94327:37"/>do you walk as <hi>Enock</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> did? and if you do, I know you would then be ſo humble, not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this prerogative; and ſo full of love to God, as to be contented to die, if it were a hundred deaths, ſo you might but enjoy him for ever: And what ſay you now? is there not a root of unbelief at the bottom? is there not ſomething of Atheiſm in this? hath not the world a prevailing intereſt in your affections? do you think you have not had time enough yet to ſin? would you ſain diſpleaſe God a little more? do you imagine that you have not ſufficiently abuſed his goodneſs? if not, what is the matter? O I want Aſſurance! did I but know that I am indeed recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, then, O then I could die as willingly as ſleep! The truth of it is, there can be no other reaſon that can bear any great weight, except this, and a deſire to glorifie God more in bringing in ſouls to him. As for this latter, I wave it; few of my hearers being ſo much concerned in that, as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are; but as for the former, I would upon this account put you upon the moſt ſpeedy and ſerious diligence in this work. I believe the Apoſtle had ſome reaſon on his ſide, when he did ſo earneſtly perſwade the people of God to uſe all diligence to make their Calling and Election ſure, and to work out their own ſalvation with fear and trembling. Why then ſhould not every Chriſtian without delay ſet upon this? And then the next news we ſhould hear would be, Come Lord Jeſus, why are thy Chariot wheels ſo long a coming? O that I might but come to eternal life, though thorough the valley of the ſhadow of death! 'Tis our trifling with God that makes the thoughts of our appearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him to be ſo dreadful. Our formality, deadneſs
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94327:38"/>and coldneſs, our worldly mindedneſs and lazineſs, doth us a world of injury. This, this diſturbeth our peace, this ſtrengthens Satan, and blurs our evidences, and makes us go deſponding into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other world, and this brings me to the next Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">USE </seg>5</label> Is it ſo that they are bleſſed that die in the Lord, &amp;c. be hence exhorted, to live ſo as that you may die in the Lord. Will you take ſo much pains for a little gains in this life, and will you take none at all for eternal bleſſings? How many hazardous voyages have ſome of you made to <hi>Ginnee,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> to get Gold and Spices? how many terrible ſtorms have you been in, and what incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable hazards have you run, that you might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy your ſelves in age, and have ſomething to carry you comfortably and decently to your graves? O why ſhould you not be as ſolicitous in your ſoul concerns? Remember my dear friends, that you are bound for another world, and you muſt ere long ſail into the Ocean of eternity. Conſider what your laiding is, and whether it will return to any account when you come home to your great Owner. Methinks you of all men ſhould think Grace the beſt commodity, and Chriſtianity the beſt trade, and the ſecuring of everlaſting happineſs, the greateſt wiſdom. How can you live within a few inches of death, and look the King of terrours in the face every day, without ſome well-grounded evidences of your intereſt in Gods love? O who would not labour to get out of danger? who would not think
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94327:38"/>it a bleſſed eſtate to be beyond fears? who can take it to be an unneceſſary work to ſecure a ſoul? is not this the one thing needful? what ſhould a man get if he ſhould gain the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul? and what ſhall a man give in exchange for his ſoul? But you Profeſſors, above all, it concerns you to make as ſure as can be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, of ſomething better than you can have here below. What a lamentable thing would it be for you to undergo ſo many reproaches for Chriſts ſake, to venture your liberties, and to hazard your eſtates, and after all to be left in woful uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? It would be a dreadful thing to loſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of both worlds. O make ſure work! your pains and coſt here will pay its own charges; be not daunted, 'tis a thing hath been done; what do you ſay? will you take ſome pains in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining of your heart? will you keep any guard over your ſelf? will you wreſtle for this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? O what courage and comfort ſhould you be endowed with! with what a chearful coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance may you meet death? and how quietly lie down in your grave, being ſupported with the hopes of a bleſſed Eternity, and a glorious Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall a little alter my diſcourſe, and turn my ſelf to the careleſs ones of the world, which think little of death, and leſs of eternity. I had occaſion before to bewail your condition, and now I might renew my lamentations, as fearing that what I have ſpoke, or may ſpeak, will have very little operation upon you; but however I cannot leave you thus, but I muſt try once more, how a plain compaſſionate exhortation will prevail. O
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94327:39"/>hat I could tell what words to ſpeak, that might each your heart! O that I could expreſs my ſelf in ſuch melting words that might break the very ſtones! O that you may feel this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</p>
            <p>Men, Brethren, and Fathers, give me leave to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you underſtand how dearly I love you, and to ſhew my affections in the moſt real de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations that may be. Sirs, I am come to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of you for Gods ſake, to be willing to live; I beſeech you deſpiſe not the bleſſing, but accept Chriſt and ſalvation while they are offered. Were it a thing poſſible to be happy any other way but by Chriſt and a holy life, I ſhould ſpare my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. If Glory could be obtained upon eaſier terms than the Goſpel ſpeaks of, I ſhould eaſe my ſelf and you of this trouble. And if any were like to be bleſſed after death, but ſuch as die in the Lord, I ſhould be the more indifferent in this matter; but ſince that cannot be, methinks thoſe three weighty words, Life, death, eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhould have a mighty influence upon you. O let not a day paſs without a few ſerious thoughts of this! I need hot perſwade you to love your lives, nature teacheth you to do that; but there is another life, which is hid from the world, which moſt forget; O think of that! that's a life indeed, a life of joy, happineſs and pleaſure! Death ſounds oft in the ears; every paſſing bell tells you, that your breath is going, and that your turn is coming, and all the Coſlins that are carried by your doors, ſay, prepare, do your work quickly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will ſhortly be too late. But who underſtands the meaning of this Preacher? who takes any thought
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94327:39"/>of another life, makes ready for death, and looks into eternity? O Eternity! Eternity! how rarely do men think of Eternity! O that now ſome would begin to be wiſe! Do you think your Sun will never ſet? will your ſands be never ran out? and do you know what dying is? then the keepers of the houſe will tremble, the windows ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hut, and inſtead of the Daughters of Muſick, the voice of groaning, lamentation and weeping. It may be death will lay his cold hand firſt upon thy feet, and bind them, and they are as cold as the earth, and what a damp doth this put upon thy ſpirit? and then you cry, once more ſend for the Doctor, and he comes in haſte. O Sir, a world for breath, half my eſtate to preſerve my life a day or two longer; and what anſwer doth he make? Sir, 'tis but a folly to flatter you, all the art in the world will not keep you alive two hours longer; what did you ſend for me for, to a dead man? and ſo he flings away in a rage; and how doth the fainting Patient hear ſuch tidings! O what ſhall I do! what, will all forſake me? can no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy help me? well, ſend for a Miniſter, and what ſaith he, Sir, how have you lived? did you pray in your family? do you know experimentally what Regeneration is? what do you ſay? Sir, I do not underſtand that word: What, did you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear a Sermon in your life? were you born in <hi>England?</hi> To be regenerated is to be born again; do you know what that is? O no, that's impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible! Why then, Sir, you are in a lamentable condition indeed; you cannot live an hour longer; and if you die in this ſtate, you muſt go to Hell as ſure as God is in Heaven. O how doth that word
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94327:40"/>ſtrike the man to the heart! and what a flame hath he within! and what horrour is his ſoul filled with! It cannot be imagined what Agonies the ſoul as well as the body now labours under. O that I might die the death of the Righteous! and are all my hopes come to this? woe, woe, woe to me poor wretch, whither am I now going? where ſhall I now dwell? who ſhall be my companions for ever? O that I had but now a little of that grace which I deſpiſed in others! but it's now too late! O my heart, I am pained at my heart! O my breath it is going, it is juſt a going! O what ſhall I do! O 'tis too late! O what ſhall—And thus his breath goes, and his friends come round about him, and one lifts up his hand, and that falls down again like a log, and others feel upon his noſe, and there's no breath, and then they ſay he is gone, and ſo one cloſeth his eyes, and others ſtrip him, and lay him out, and two daies after he is put into the grave: but where, where is the ſoul? And thus one goes after another, and ſhortly all this generation will be ſerved thus. And thou, O careleſs ſoul, as little as thou mindeſt all this, it may be thou mayeſt be the next, and what will become of thee if death take thee unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided! Now Sirs, what will you do? will you go on juſt as you did? will you put far from you the thoughts of the evil day? will you ſhake off the ſenſe of this as ſoon as you can? I believe that this is none of the pleaſanteſt diſcourſes to ſome of you: But I would have you to know that my buſineſs is not to pleaſe your fancy, but to ſave your ſouls, and to wake you out of your dead ſleep; and if I do but this, I have enough. Once
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:94327:40"/>more therefore I muſt ask you what you intend to do; will you indeavour to live to Chriſt, that you may die in the Lord? or will you do as others do, put off the thoughts of theſe things till it be too late? Is this a queſtion ſo hard to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered? Well, methinks the very looks of ſome of you ſpeak you to be perſons reſolved, and by this time you are ready to ask how you ſhall do to be of this number that ſhall die in the Lord, and be bleſſed; how you may trade ſo as to get the moſt durable riches; and how you may live ſo as to gain by death? In general I anſwer, If you would have death gain, you muſt live to Chriſt; make it your work and buſineſs to ſecure an intereſt in Chriſt; let Religion run thorow all you do; (but for your fuller information in this matter, I ſhall refer you to the latter end of my Book of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God, which is now reprinted) at preſent my advice ſhall be, that you would follow them who thorow faith and patience are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriters of the promiſe; and propoſe to your ſelves the examples of the moſt eminent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; ſuch as this precious young mans, whoſe Funeral Rites we are now ſolemnizing; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe examples are very cogent, and affect moſt, more than precepts, I ſhall preſent you with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome of this holy young mans practices and experiences: Take them therefore as I have gathered them by my own experience and intimate knowledge of him; and as I have collected them out of many ſheets of his own writings. But let it not be thought, I beſeech you, that out of cuſtom or flattery, I ſpeak ſuch Funeral Commendations: were he but a Common Chriſtian, I would have
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94327:41"/>ſorb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rn ſpeaking any thing of this nature for ſear of hardening ſinners. I muſt deal plainly, I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ho that curſed flattery in commending all that are buried; as if to die and to go to Heaven were all one. I know many rotten poſts are guilded; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sepulchres that are full of bones, and putrified fleſh, are painted, and many Profeſſors are extolled at their death, who did no good wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le they lived, except it were the giving ſome pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the poor when they could keep it no longer. I queſtion not but that thouſands are praiſed upon earth, that are condemned in Heaven; and many applauded for Saints, that will be found among the Devils and damned. Expect it not therefore as a thing like to be uſual with me to commend dead perſons. As I would judge none, ſo I dare commend but few. This only by way of Apology. I ſhall come to the thing promiſed, to propoſe ſome imitable paſſages of the life of <hi>T. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, He began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook Heaven ward betimes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he was made to remember his Creatour in the daies of his youth; his firſt conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions were at about twelve years old, but they had no abiding impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon him, the great work was begun to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe between ſeven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een and eighteen. I ſhall be the more brief here, becauſe you have the account more full from his own hand. The change that was wrought upon him did expreſs more of the power of God, and the riches of his grace than ordinary. The Lord made his work upon him very clear and diſtinct; for he broke in upon his ſoul like an armed man, and ſhook him terribly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hell, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs of God ſet themſelves
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94327:41"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n array againſt him, and the poiſon of his arrows drank up his ſpirits, ſin did appear in its colour to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ugly as the devil, and as dreadful as <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf; ſo that the foundation was laid in very deep hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lity. O then how frightful a thing was ſin, yea his beloved ſin, the ſin of gaming was made moſt loathſome and abominable, ſo that for that he loathed himſelf in duſt aſhes, and looked upon himſelf as unworthy to tread upon Gods ground, and had not God ordered it ſo as that the firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon he heard after this great conviction was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. he had even fallen into deſpair, but the thoughts of Gods having mercy upon the chiefeſt of ſinners, did a little ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his ſoul, and gave him hopes of a poſſibility of being ſaved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This put him upon ſtrong groans and prayers, that the Lord would pitty him as ever he would pitty any poor creature in the World, O that he would pitty him; haſt thou not a bleſſing for me, O God even for me, what ſhall I do, now I am without God, Chriſt, or Grace, my condition is ſuch I cannot bear it, who can be contented to be damned! O pitty me, pitty me, dear Lord, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what in the world to do; mercy, mercy, mercy, or I am loſt, mercy ſpeedily or I am loſt for ever: And ſo he continued in a way of duty, reading, and praying, and inquiring, and reſolving thus to do all his dayes; and now farewell wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed company, farewell ſports and vanity and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the great buſineſs of minding his ſoul now ſwallows him up, and after a while he hath a little more peace than he had, but upon further enquiry
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94327:42"/>and waiting upon the means, he was convinced tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all this would not do without the Righteouſneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt: And this brings me to the next thing,</p>
            <p n="3">3. He was deeply convinced of the abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and excellency of Chriſt, and brought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from his own righteouſneſs, to high prizing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and admirings of Chriſt; take his own words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <q>And is it true indeed, hath Chriſt done and ſuffered ſuch things for thee, O my poor ſinful, vile, odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous polluted ſoul, and what wilt not thou love him now? Oh think a little what put him upon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this, was it any ſelf intereſt, is he any gainer by thee, he got nothing but grief, pain and death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O my ſoul it was free, pure and undeniable love that cauſed him to do and ſuffer what he did conſider again O my ſoul, what cauſe was there that he ſhould make thee a partaker of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his blood, what waſt thou, Oh a mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loathſome ſinner, and what wilt thou not yet love him? O Lord, I am aſhamed of my own heart, that I cannot raiſe it to the higheſt pitch o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> admiration of that infinite boundleſs love. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> love, love, love; O that I could love thee, O Lord, I would fain be ſick of love, O that I could dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſick of love to thee, O that I could feel thee warming my heart with that quickning blood which thou ſheddedſt upon the Croſs; O what love is like to that; O my ſoul, it was ſhed for thee who was an enemy, a rebel, a deſpiſer of Chriſt! awake O bleſſed ſpirit and blow upon my ſoul, and kindle a fire which may burn with love to Chriſt, to all Eternity, Amen, Amen.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:94327:42"/>
            <p n="4">4. He did upon this in a ſerious and ſolemn manner give up himſelf to the Lord in a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, (I ſhall not repeat the words of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, becauſe they are taken verbatim out of my book of Acquaintance with God) and he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cribed his name to it, and kept it as a witneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and to quicken his own ſoul to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore cloſe walking with God according to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cles of that Covenant.</p>
            <p n="5">5. After he was gone thus far, his bowels began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o yern over his Chriſtleſs friends, ſome of which (I perceive by his letters) began to abuſe him for his ſeriouſneſs, and to deride his ſtrictneſs and jeer at his holineſs: ſhall I give you a taſte of his ſpirit, I cannot do it in warmer words than his own which are as followeth.—</p>
            <p>
               <q>Yours I received, but whether I dare to thank you for it, I know not, for truly I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the trouble that hath ſince ſeiſed upon my ſpirit; Oh poor ſoul, what ſhall I ſay unto thee? Oh my bowels, my bowels, they yern towards thee, I am pained, yea I am pained while I think upon thy condition, what ſhall I do for thee, what ſhall I ſay unto thee; I could be contented that theſe lines were writ with my very heart blood, ſo that they might affect thee; O I had rather dye than receive another ſuch letter from you, I could not reliſh it, it was bitter, I could not ſee the name of dear Jeſus in it, — how can I think of your blind ſuperſtition, and not mourn and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over a dead ſoul! you ſay you are ſorry, and you are troubled. What is the matter, are you ſorry that I ſhould concern my ſelf about my ſoul,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94327:43"/>and about yours; you would not trouble your ſelf about theſe things now, if not now, I pray when will you, at the hour of death, at the day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Judgement, O then it will be too late, O now o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> never, delayes are dangerous. O Eternity, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, O where ſhall yours and my ſoul dwell t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all Eternity. Oh either in heaven, or in hell, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Chriſt or devils, the ſoul that ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall dye; your debt is great, the juſtice of God muſt be ſatisfied, and nothing can do it but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blood of Jeſus, O for this precious Jeſus, make not light of Chriſt, he is precious, he is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovely; I would not for ten thouſand world quit my ſhare in him, and in that which is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your fear, you complain that I have le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the wayes of our fore-fathers — I ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you take the ſhadow for the ſubſtance; what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Croſs in Baptiſm, without the Baptiſme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpirit; what good will the bowing at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> name of Jeſus do them, which perſecute him i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his members, and have him not formed in their hearts — O that God would cut aſunder your falſe hopes, if Chriſt were in you, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would rejoyce to think that he hath been a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> work in my ſoul, was I born with theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which you read in my laſt Letters, I am ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I was once of an other mind than now I am<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but bleſſed, yea admired be free grace, which hath made me to differ from my ſelf and others. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> am afraid you underſtand not my meaning, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I ſpeak of love to God and Regeneration, as long as I only concerned my ſelf about the World, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not my ſoul, you kindly entertained my letters but no ſooner did I ſpeak of repentance, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:94327:43"/>affairs of our poor never-dying ſouls, but then you are troubled and cannot bear it. I tell you I lay dead almoſt eighteen years, and then I had a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wound from my dear God, which made me cry out where am I, I am undone, I am undone, my ſin will damn me. O what ſhall I do for a Chriſt — And at this rate he goes on writing many letters, which did all breath a divine ſpirit.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. He was very ſpiritual in his diſcourſe, and by that he put life into moſt of them that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with him; how helpful was he to young Chriſtians! how ready to hearten them up in the wayes of God, and how able to diſcover to them the policies of Satan! he was ſcarce in his element, but when he was doing or receiving of good, he ſtudied Mr. <hi>Herbert Palmer</hi>'s little Book about making Religion ones buſineſs, and he did in a great meaſure put it into practice: To uſe his own expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <q>I did, ſaith he, labour to ſpiritualize com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon action, and to ſerve God in ſerving my maſter with diligence, cheerfulneſs and faithfulneſs.</q> O what reſort was there of young ones to him for direction and advice in things which they did not think it ſo fit to trouble their Paſtor with, and how did he endeavour to ſeaſon his fellow ſervants with grace: When he went to any of his Maſters Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, how diligent in uſing of means for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and how careful to drop ſomething that might tend to the health of their ſouls, and as he had opportunity amongſt the weaker and poorer ſort, he would pray with them, and O with what vehemency of ſpirit, with what fluency of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and with what mighty affections would he do
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:94327:44"/>it? I need not tell ſome of you, how helpfull he hath been to the bodies and ſouls of the ſick, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account he looked upon it as a great mercy that the Lord had called him to ſuch an employment, wherein he had ſuch ſingular advantages to deal with poor ſouls about the affairs of Eternity: I queſtion no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but there are ſome ſtanding here that have cauſe to bleſs God that ever they ſaw his face, and I believe that ſome of you that are young and poor will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dearly miſs him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He was exceedingly raiſed in duty and one that injoyed rare communion, intimacy and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God; and for about five moneths (as his own papers ſhew) together, he rarely came into the preſence of God, but he went away with ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial tokens of his love; ſo that he ſaid he could have been contented to have left the world at a quarter of an hours warning: Hear how his Papers ſpeak; <q>My ſoul continued (if my heart do not mightily deceive me) in a thriving condition for five moneths. O the comforts that I then had, they are unſpeakable, I ſeldome went to duty, but carryed my dear Saviour, and brought him away with me; every Ordinance was a viſit of love; my love to Jeſus Chriſt, and his members whereever I ſaw them was not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; what hatred to ſin, what zeal for Gods glory, what yerning of bowels towards poor ſouls in the ſtate of nature, how beautiful were the feet of the Embaſſadors of peace, what a fulneſs and ſweetneſs did I then ſee and feel in Chriſt, ever hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring after him, and ever ſatisfied with him, and him alone, what affections. God-ward, what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing of viſibles, what deep apprehenſions of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94327:44"/>Majeſty and Attributes of God, how did I walk un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weariedly with him, how did I rejoyce before him with fear, and truſt filially in him with trembling! O what watchfulneſs over my thoughts, words and actions: Indeed I was often aſſaulted, but I had a faithful Centinel which would give warning, and admit of none but ſuch as were friends to the Lord Jeſus; what low thoughts had I of my ſelf, and high prizings of a naked Chriſt! Oh Sir, in one word I made Religion my buſineſs, and was taken up with that which concerned the glory of God; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace was at ſtrife which ſhould excell other in its actings; I could never go to market, but I could experience returns of Grace and Mercy.</q> In this I have not varied two words from his own writings in a letter that he gave me, wherein he did grievouſly bewail the leaſt departures of his heart from God, as you ſhall hear in the next.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He took ſpecial notice of his own heart, and did mightily bewail any declinings from that vigour that ſometimes he had; and here I ſhall again uſe his words as they follow— <q>But this did not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long, it was as a calm before a ſtorm, for ſoon after (my time being almoſt out) I began to have ſome thoughts of my ſetting up and entring into the world; but I had no ſooner imbraced the motion, but that very day I felt a change in my poor ſoul, <hi>viz.</hi> a too too much letting out my thoughts upon it, which I moſt perceived in duty, and the devil who long waited his opportunity, did then, I am afraid, not only parley, but get entrance, through the treachery and deceitfulneſs of my wretched heart, and he told me that I might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:94327:45"/>ſettle my mind upon this, it being a buſineſs of great concernment, and that it would be but a little while, and then I ſhould return to my former tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in ſpiritual matters, upon thoſe deluſions my ſilly heart gave way, and I found too much willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſoul to place its concerns in that matter, and ſo I laying down my watch, ſoon loſt my former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, and every day I found my comforts on the ebbing hand, I ſecretly departed from God, and darkened the light of his countenance, that did ſhine ſometimes upon my ſoul, and had not infinite grace put a ſeaſonable word into your mouth to prevent me, how had I fallen, and whither had I gone? I could not have thought it poſſible that ever my heart ſhould decline ſo ſtrangely as it did. I that formerly could ſerve my Maſter faithfully, cheerfully and comfortably, did it grutchingly, and not out of love, though I never fell ſo far, (through grace) as to neglect any thing of his buſineſſes, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loſt the right principles of action; and the art of ſpiritualizing of civil affairs; and this laſted for about three moneths; It is ſcarce to be thought what perplexities I brought my ſelf into, by my back-ſliding from God; I have not time to declare things, and had I, it would be very unwelcome to you; true, I hope I did enjoy ſome communion with God when I was engaged in duties, eſpecially in that to be admired Ordinance of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Prayer; but yet my comforts and duty uſually ended together, I hope the experience that I have had of the treachery of my own heart, will make me carry a fence of my weakneſs and folly, ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> throw my ſelf wholly upon the wiſdom of God — I have thus opened my ſoul to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94327:45"/>you, O that the Lord, who firſt for his own name ſake ſhewed mercy to me when I deſerved none, would now look upon me in my low eſtate, and conſult the ſame bowels of pitty and compaſſion, which are infinite, paſt the ſins of finite creatures; O that he would heal my back-ſlidings, and love me freely: God is the ſame, and changeth not, and my hopes are that he will again return and viſit my ſoul in mercy —</q> After this the Lord was pleaſed to come in again, and he found his former comforts in ſome meaſure returning after a great deal of pains with his own heart, and wreſtling with God: Hear what language he begins to ſpeak again,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Bleſſed be God for what I do enjoy, it is ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more than I deſerve, I hope the dew of the ſanctuary doth oft refreſh me, and the blood of Jeſus is my cordial, when I ſit at his Table, he viſits me, and his banner over me is love. I may ſpeak it to the glory of rich grace, that my heart is in a better frame than it was, and I am more free from diſtractions in duty, but yet I am far from that frame that I was once in, my diſtemper it lyeth in want of thoſe ſtrong affections to God: and that which hath made me ſo ſilent to you is the fear of hypocriſie; leſt my tongue ſhould at any time out-reach my heart.</q> I might be far larger, and yet ſpeak none but his words, this I think may prove that he was a very curious obſerver of his own ſoul, and took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the leaſt departures of his heart from God, or Gods abſenting of himſelf from him. I might tell you what pains he took to prepare for the Sacrament, and what exactneſs he uſed afterwards in taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice how his ſoul was affected, &amp; when it was not rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, what care did he uſe till he found a freſh w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nth,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94327:46"/>heat and life animating of him, I might tell you how frequent he was in that rare duty of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; I ſpeak not this without book, many ſheets of his meditations which I have by me ſhew that he was no ſtranger to thoſe ſpiritual duties which few underſtand and fewer practiſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He was greatly deſirous to be reproved and watched over, that of the Pſalmiſt was oft in his mouth, and written in his Letter, Let the Righteous ſmite me, and it ſhall be a kindneſs, and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove me, and it ſhall be excellent Oyl, which ſhall not break my head.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He was much exerciſed in acts of mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſelf denyal, he laboured to keep under his body, to have the command of his paſſions and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, very temperate, drinking water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. He was frequently praiſing of God and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well of his wayes; indeed his deportment was ſuch that he credited Religion, and commended the ſervice of his great Maſter, and made people to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Religion was an excellent thing, and he juſtified wiſdom, and was able to ſay her wayes were pleaſantneſs, and her paths peace.</p>
            <p n="12">12. He was a very good Husband of time, one would wonder, how one could roll over ſuch a deal of buſineſs as he did, not in the leaſt neglecting his Maſters affairs, and yet that he ſhould write ſuch packets of letters, and pen ſo many Meditations, and be ſo very helpful to his brethren the young men: How many Books did he read over, and read
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:94327:46"/>them to the purpoſe, ſo as to make them his own, ſome of them five or ſix times over; and if he had no company to dicourſe with, when he went abroad, he lookt oft into his Pocket Book, which was called, Making Religion ones buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="13">13. He had a ſtrong affection for the faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and was concerned when the Cloud began to threaten them, that he ingaged all the Prayers he could for them that the Lord would blow over this ſtorm, and I am ready to think that this might haſten his end.</p>
            <p n="14">14. He was greatly afraid of ſpiritual pride, to this end; he deſired me to keep a watch over him, and beſeeched me to diſcover it to him, when I did at any time diſcern the actings of it, but though he had great parts and gifts above his age, yet the fence of former ſins, and his curious obſervance of his heart, and the fence of free grace, kept him very low.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He ſeemed to be poſſeſſed with the thoughts of death and Eternity. He had a ſtrong impreſſion upon his ſpirit of the neerneſs of his end for about half a year before he dyed. And,</p>
            <p n="16">16. He was much above the fears of death, and from a deep fence of the reallity of inviſibles, and his propriety in them; he thought long for poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and he could ſay I deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Jeſus.</p>
            <p>On the Lords Day before he dyed he was in an extaſie of comfort, and felt what thoſe joyes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable in believing meant, in former times he had
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94327:47"/>great manifeſtations of Gods love, but never any broke into his ſoul with ſuch power, and clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as then; he had as it were a proſpect of glory, and ſome foretaſtes of that happineſs that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him before the foundations of the world; and O how did his heart even leap within him to think that within a little while he ſhould fully and eternally enjoy what he now had a little glympſe of. —</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Munday</hi> I went to viſit him, and found him in a very ſweet frame, ſo taken up with Heaven, that he did even wonder at himſelf. I am (ſaith he) ſo overcome with the love of Chriſt and the glory of Heaven, that all manner of fear is hid from mine eyes, and I cannot ſo much as think of Hell; or if I do, it is with joy that there is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus: but what do you think of theſe things, is it poſſible that they ſhould be deluſions; O Sir, I beſeech you be faithfull to my ſoul, and tell me as you will anſwer it at the barr of God, what you judge of my ſtate; I would not for a World be now in a fools Paradice; and then he told me his experiences, and intreated me to ſearch and try him, and again and again he expreſſed his great joy under the apprehenſions of death, and that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Eternity that he was paſſing into; <q>I deſired earneſtly to diſcourſe with you (ſaid he) becauſe I expect to loſe the uſe of my reaſon, and am not like to be capable of ſpeaking my mind to you hereafter, and then he intreated me to give him a Funeral Sermon:</q> And all this he ſpoke with as much cheerfulneſs as can well be imagined, ſpeaking of death as the moſt deſirable thing; <q>O, ſaith he, that I were but ten times ſicker, I long to dye, I am
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:94327:47"/>ill, but I would be ill to purpoſe; O dear Jeſus, I long to be with thee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Tueſday,</hi> his diſtemper grew much upon him, and began a little at times to impair his intellectuals, and yet by fits he would ſpeak excellently of the things of God; being asked whether he was willing to dye, he anſwered, <q>That Eternity was too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for him to praiſe God in for his rich mercy to ſuch a poor creature as he was, that the Lord ſhould prepare ſuch an inheritance amongſt the Saints in glory for him, and that his life was hid with Chriſt, and that when Chriſt who was his life ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, he alſo ſhould appear with him in glory:</q> This morning he prayed for an exhorted thoſe that were in the family, to prepare to meet him in glory.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> when he had any intermiſſions; he broke out into ſuch expreſſions as theſe. <q>Dear Jeſus, what art thou doing, preparing Manſions for me? I am coming ſweet Jeſus, I am coming, — It is but a little while, a little thread, and when that is cut, I ſhall be ſafe in glory. Being very ill he ſaid, What if I ſhould live two hours, or two dayes, what is that to a glorious Eternity? Death, what is it but a Porter to open Heaven-gate for me? — What is all the World compared to that Crown which I ſhall receive?</q> — Being asked how he did, he anſwered very well, one ſtanding by ſaid no, you are very ill; he replyed, <q>I know I am very ſick, but I ſay I am well, becauſe I am as God would have me be.</q> When I came to him in the afternoon, I found him exceeding ill, and betraying ſome weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his intellectuals, and his diſcourſe being very impertinent; I ſaid to him, your language was wont to be ſpiritual, but now you forget your ſelf;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94327:48"/>
               <q>It is true Sir, ſaid he, but you know what the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of my body now is, bleſſed be God the root of matter is in me.</q> After this he was very ſtill and quiet whileſt I read to him, and ſeemed to be much pleaſed at the reading of the fifty fourth, and fifty fifth of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and gave a very rational account of any ſpiritual queſtion that was put to him, and very deſirous that I ſhould pray with him.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> becauſe of extraordinary buſineſs of my own I could not be preſent with him.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Friday</hi> he was taken ſpeechleſs for many hours together, but according to our Prayers at laſt he recovered the uſe of his reaſon more than before, and could ſpeak that we might well underſtand him; then I asked him how he did, he anſwered me <hi>Still alive</hi>—After a conſiderable pauſe he cryed out <hi>Gracious Father, thy Will be done.</hi> Then I opened ſeveral Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to him, which ſpeak the bleſſed ſtate of Saints in another World, and when I asked him whether he did underſtand me; He anſwered, <hi>Yes, Yes,</hi> and wept ſeveral times for joy. Now the Symptomes of death approaching come upon him, ſcarce any pulſe, and a dying ſweat, and the laſt words that I heard him ſpeak were <hi>Glory, Glory</hi> — After that he continued in very great Agonies, and his pangs were ſtrong, till about 11 of the Clock, then he ſlept in Jeſus: being exceedingly lamented by the young men of his Society, many of which were about him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:94327:48"/>
            <head>An Accompt of Gods Dealings with this Young man, before, and at his Converſion, with ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon the ſame; as it was Delivered to me under his own hand (after I had Diſcourſed with him) by way of Dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Miniſter and himſelf.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat ought to be the great care and duty of every profeſſing Chriſtian in theſe our dayes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Convert.</speaker>
               <p>Pray, What may be the reaſon of this your Queſtion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I have very many reaſons, but one is this, Becauſe it is daily ſeen that very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who have made great profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igion, and are accounted amongſt the wiſe Virgins, fall away, which is very ſad to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ider; and I fear that the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:94327:49"/>there is not that care taken about the ſtate of their ſouls which there ought to be, now I pray you anſwer me my Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> What ought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>With reſpect to the former, It ought to be every Chriſtians great care to examine himſelf whether he be in the ſtate of grace or no, and which way the Lord was pleaſed to bring him into that bleſſed condition; ſith it is to be feared the want of this is the great and chief cauſe of mans apoſtaſie from Religion, for had he ever been truly wrought upon by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, had his convictions (which more or leſs all have had) turned to a true converſion, and had his pangs of ſorrow for ſin but brought forth regeneration, then ſurely he would have been in ſuch an eſtate, from which all the malice of the powers of darkneſs could not have drawn him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>The Anſwer doth ſomewhat ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of goodneſs, and that you underſtand with your heart, what you expreſs with the tongue; converſion or regeneration is a mighty work, and on whomſoever it is truly wrought, that perſon can ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more or leſs concerning the nature of it, and how it was wrought in his ſoul; if the Lord hath in any meaſure revealed
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:94327:49"/>himſelf to you in this way, let me intreat you (both for your own ſouls good, and perhaps other ſouls good, but chiefly that the Lord may thereby be glorified) to let me know the time and manner of his draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to himſelf, by his unſpeakable love and mercy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh: Bleſſed be God that he hath opened the heart of his faithful Miniſter to demand ſuch a matter of ſuch a poor wretch as I am; oh what am I that I ſhould be examined, inſtructed and confirmed, about the matters of my eternal pretious, and never dying ſoul? Oh that the Lord would ſo enable me in this great work, that I may not be found to lye againſt the holy Ghoſt, by adding to, or diminiſhing from what I have found; but that I may have my heart and conſcience witneſſing within me, that theſe following things are ſo indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad to hear what you have ſaid, and the Lord bring all things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our preſent work into your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that his name may be glorified and your ſoul much comforted; and to this end it will be requiſite to demand of you, What condition are you in by nature?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>O Sir, A rebel to my God, a ſlave to my luſt, a prodigal to my Father, an
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:94327:50"/>alien from the Common-Wealth of Iſrael; in ſhort had I dyed in my natural ſtate; I had been eternally miſerable, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. <hi>except,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How long did you continue in that deplorable condition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh too too long, but yet bleſſed be God, and admired be free Grace, that it was no longer, it was as neer as I can gueſs eighteen years and a few dayes, when the Lord did incline my heart in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to ſeek the things of its everlaſting peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Well, and how then did the Lord begin with you; were your eyes never opened to ſee your loſt undone condition before that time?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh yes, when I was twelve or thirteen years of age, the Lord diſcovered my condition ſo much to me, that I did then firmly believe, all that did ſerve the Lord were in a very bleſſed and happy eſtate, let what come as could come they were happy, and likewiſe that if I ſhould then have dyed, I ſhould have been eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſerable; having no hopes in Chriſt, neither did I in that condition expect any benefit by him; and as I very well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the Lord made the thoughts of death ſo terrible, that I could not endure to think
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:94327:50"/>of it, but yet it came ſo much in my mind, and did ſo terrifie me, that I cannot expreſs how I did dread to think of it, but this worked nothing in me, but (oh with horrour and amazement be it ſpoken) I was willing then to go to hell, and did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in that I could quell my gripes of conſcience, by thinking that I ſhould be as well able to endure the flames of hell and the frowns of an angry God as any of them all, and that I ſhould have company enough there, and ſo did rejoyce becauſe I was willing to be damned, willing to be damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; how, what did I ſay? but ſurely I was not; oh my ſoul, how can it be? make' anſwer; was it ſo? yes, and was I, oh was I indeed willing to be damned, oh the height, and length, and breadth, and depth of the love, and goodneſs, and long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing patience of an offended and highly provoked God, that I was not then thrown into hell indeed; but that he ſhould ſuffer ſuch ſtubble as I was to be in his ſight, and that the fire of his Jealouſie had not conſumed me as in a moment, but ſtill I went on in ſin, as if I would not have let God alone till he had damned me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>By what you have ſaid, I perceive then you were throughly convinced of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:94327:51"/>the neceſſity of holineſs, and of leaving your ſins, and ſerving the Lord, and that there muſt be Regeneration wrought in you, before Glorification could be hoped for by you; but ſurely being convinced of the bleſſed condition of the godly, you could not but ſometimes wiſh your ſelf in their condition; how did you carry your ſelf under this, did you reſolve that you would never be as they were?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Truly, many times I would have been glad to have been in their condition, but I was ſo glued to the world, and my ſins, that I could not endure to think of leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, yet (to my beſt remembrance) I never reſolved that if I ſhould live never ſo long I would not repent, but that after I had gotten a great eſtate in the world, and was grown old, and were as it were uncapable of taking any more delight in theſe things below, that then I would have ſet out towards Heaven, and oh I cannot but think (and I deſire with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to think) what a loathſome Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice I ſhould then have been, even ſtunk in Gods noſtrils, when I had given the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fatneſs and ſtrength of my body to the devil; then I ſhould have had juſt cauſe to fear the Lord would have buryed me out of his ſight; Oh I ſay, I ſtaid in the devils
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:94327:51"/>ſervice ſo long, that I ſmelt ſo of fire and brimſtone, I mean of ſin, that had not the body of a Crucified Advocate Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, as a Vail, ſtood between the Juſtice of God and my guilty ſoul, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he would ſoon have drawn out a bill of indictment againſt me, and have ſent me away with a <hi>Go ye Curſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>By what you have ſaid I perceive you lay under Convictions for about 6 years, with very little grief or ſorrow for ſin, but although you knew what you were to do, yet you did not do what you did know: I will ask you but one' queſtion more before I come to the chief point in hand, and that is this; What duties you engaged in in this time, and how you carryed your ſelf under them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Now, even now, I begin to revel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from my promiſe, but that I might if po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible debaſe my ſelf below the vileſt cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the world, I will declare ſomethi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and enough to make your very hair to ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an end, and oh that the Lord would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make me ſo reflect upon my ſelf, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may abhor my wretched ſelf in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aſhes, for (oh Lord) if this w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what will? for the greater part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 06 years I lived without Prayer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Scripture, but ſeldom miſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:94327:52"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y reaſon of my civil education; and as to Prayer, (but why ſhould I call it ſo) ſcarce ever did I deſire that the Lord ſhould hear me; nay I did often in my heart deſire to the contrary, nay more, when I have been upon my knees, and my conſcience hath conſtrained me to ſay prayer, I have ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly received an inward motion to this effect, that God at that time was a mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other affairs, and that then I might to bed and he not mind me; at which moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I did, and ſo left off for that time, and at all times performed them againſt my will; Oh horrible Blaſphemy, what, not God ſee; Oh it was a wonder of wonders, that God ſhould then have endured to ſee me any longer out of Hell: (oh infinite patience) as for reading I got little good by it, and deſired to get leſs, and as for hearing I muſt confeſs that thoſe arrows ſhot at a venture, God did cauſe them ſo many times to hit, yea and peirce too, that it buſied both me and the devil to get them out again, and to heal the wound; but uſually I fixed my mind upon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe, ſo that I ſeldome let any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſink too deep into my heart; yea once the Devil and my own wicked heart did ſo ſar prevail, that I was fully reſolved, and in plain, but damnable terms, I did
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:94327:52"/>even curſe God, and as it were bid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to all his Ordinances, and did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce that I had my tongue and conſcience ſo much at command; (oh and how can I hold my pen to write this! wherefore do I not fall down and become nothing before the Lord of Glory againſt whom thus I have blaſphemed; but truly I would not have revealed this, had I not ſuch a place as the 12. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the 31. <hi>verſe</hi> to make to for a refuge.) After this I was wont to put that ſolemn Ordinance of Prayer to do the ſaddeſt ſervice in the world, and that frequently, (O pitty, pitty it had ſuch a cruel Maſter,) and that was, I uſed it not to help me to deſtroy ſin, but made it a greater cauſe and means of my ſinning; for I had got the damnable Art (as they ſay, the Papiſts have at this day, only I did not get ſo much by it as their Father Confeſſors doth) that if I had ſaid but two or three ſhort ejaculations, not with half the devotion that a <hi>Pater noſter</hi> is ſaid, yea I ſay, I had got that curſed Art to reſiſt all gripes of conſcience, and to ſin freely for a month or more; and when conſcience would let me alone no longer, then to prayer again. Oh Adamantine heart, or rather ſtone, that canſt hold out to write theſe things, and not to quake and tremble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:94327:53"/>And now, <hi>de his quid dicam?</hi> theſe are the <hi>peccata peccatorum,</hi> but what, is that ſoul ſtill alive that hath done theſe things? what, ſhall a poor worm curſe God and not die? what, blaſpheme the Ordinances of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and ſtill live? ſure the Jealouſie of a holy God will not ſuffer ſuch a wretch to be in his ſight: But tell me, is this man alive? or hath the earth ſwallowed him up? or the flames of hell caught hold of him? certainly had he thus offended his fellow-worms, they could not have born it, and can I think that God will ſuffer ſuch a man, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Devil incarnated, to live in his ſight? Oh my ſoul, make anſwer, what alive? yes, yes; but how is he? hath he not his conſcience ſeared? and is not his condemnation ſealed within himſelf? and what, doth he not look with horrour and amazement for the great day of the Lord? No, my hopes are to the contrary: Nay, I hope, and not without cauſe, that him hath the Lord ſet apart for himſelf, and to his poor ſoul hath he ſhewed ſuch mercies, that it will make all that hear of it to admire, and to ſay, What is man that thou ſhouldeſt be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of him? but that the Lord ſhould pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſuch a loathſome creature as this, and ſhould ſay to ſuch a vile brat then wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its blood live; Oh come, come unto
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:94327:53"/>me all ye that fear the Lord; Oh come unto me, and I will tell you what he hath done for my ſoul; he that is mighty hath done for me great things, yea almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible things, and holy is his Name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Well (poor ſoul) I will no longer detain thee concerning theſe things, but now you having given me a very doleful account of your long convictions, yet ſtill lying bound with the chains of ſin, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of Satan, which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs had it gone no further, but you had ended your life before the Lord had turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your convictions into converſion, it would have proved ſuch a worm, that would to all eternity have gnawed thy conſcience, ſo that the pains would have been intollerable; but (bleſſed be God) I am in great hopes to hear that from you, which will put me out of fear, and give me cauſe to admire the goodneſs and power of God: Be very careful to keep your heart from pride, and not to attribute any thing to your own goodneſs, but to admire the grace of God, and give glory to him, and him alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh (dear friend) for ſo I will call you, and all that gives me counſel about the good of my never dying ſoul, I am glad that the Lord hath put this into
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:94327:54"/>yourheart, and I do beg your prayers to God that he would ſtill humble me more and more; for I am ſure pride is a weed that will grow in the beſt garden, much more in mine, which is a barren, yet weedy ſoil; but I have not done with all my ſoul-abaſing conſiderations, for when you have heard all (which I through the grace of God am to declare unto you) you will then ſay, I have more cauſe to be humbled than ever; therefore pride being ſuch an enemy, I will earneſtly requeſt you, that when you hear me ſay any thing which doth ſavour of my own good, and not purely of Gods Glory, that you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove me, and make me clear my meaning to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I have ſtill more cauſe to bleſs God for you, in that you do ſo much ſuſpect your own heart, which is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked and deceitful. And now to our preſent purpoſe; what reaſon have you to think, that your converſion was more effectually begun to be wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, when you was about eighteen years of age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, I have great cauſe to think ſo; for then the Lord was pleaſed to work ſuch a work in me, that had it been told me before, I could not in any wiſe have believed it.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:94327:54"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>And now, what do you think to be the firſt cauſe that moved you to ſet your face Sion-ward?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>About two months before I ſaw the ſinfulneſs of ſin, even then when I was to every good word and work a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and did deny no ſin, becauſe it was ſin, although I might out of ſome ſelf ends, as to deny theft, whoredom, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſuch like; not that theſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were ſo deteſtable to me, but for fear of outward trouble I did not practiſe them; but being engaged in a great ſin, which was gaming, which ſome may ſcruple, whether it may be a ſin or no; but to me I am ſure it was the occaſion of many great ſins, as to cauſe me to ſwear and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear, and to lye, and cheat in great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and truly I think my heart at that time was ſo deſperately wicked, that doubtleſs, had not an Almighty Power pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, I ſhould even have pawned my ſoul, for the obtaining of what I then deſired, then in a paſſion I made a preſumptuous vow, that I would leave off that ſport for one year; this was about <hi>November</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> which for a little time I kept; and now obſerve the great ſubtilty of the Devil in this particular, for no ſooner was it the firſt day of <hi>January,</hi> but preſently I was
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:94327:55"/>told that my vow was out of date, and that it ſignified nothing; and they being my carnal friends that told me, I was willing to make my conſcience ſubmit, ſo that I ſoon embraced my old ſport again, and did plainly lay my ſelf open to the wrath of God for ſuch a great ſin; yet I could not ſo much charm my conſcience, but it would often accuſe me for it; but it was not many weeks after, but I engaged as deeply in the ſame ſin of gaming as before (and now hear and admire, for even now will appear ſuch love, as never any was ever ſenſible of, but ſuch as have felt it) having been at the loſing hand, the ſeaſon of the night calling me away, I left off, but much troubled, and about five in the morning I awakened, and then there was a pleaſant lightneſs upon my ſpirit, as if it had been refreſhed after great trouble; what this meant I could not tell, yet could not but take ſpecial notice of it, that I who went to bed much diſſatisfied and perplexed, ſhould, when I awaked, ſeem to be ſo much comforted, and my ſleep for a little time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from me, and certainly I had ſome deep thoughts, which now I cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; but the reſult of them came to this, I did then engage my ſelf by a freſh vow, that the next morning I would play ſo as
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:94327:55"/>to venture about two ſhillings, and if I loſt that, then not to play any more for ſuch a certain time, and to my beſt remembrance, (for as I would not add, ſo I would not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, and ſo rob God of his glory, and my poor ſoul of comfort) I did at that time lift up my heart to God (but with what affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions I cannot tell, I hope not without great ſhame) to crave his aid that I might be enabled to keep my great vow; and ſo when the time came that I was to venture my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which I thought very long, with great chearfulneſs I went to play, being very willing, and I think deſirous to loſe, which was ſoon accompliſhed according to my hopes; which when it was ended, I cannot ſay what I thought, or how my heart work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but as I think that very day my heart was ſomewhat troubled by what follows; for I having loſt a great part of that in which my heart ſo much delighted, and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized as its God, and reſted in as its ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end, I could not find reſt in it as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; and ſo being much troubled, I went to peruſe ſome toyes that I had by me, and amongſt them there was one Jewel, which the Lord was pleaſed to put into my hand, (which was a Book intituled, <hi>The Crumbs of Comfort</hi>) the which, when I felt my heart ſomewhat inclined to peruſe, I was much
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:94327:56"/>perplexed within my ſelf, and could not but wonder what manner of ſalutation this ſhould be; and now I hope I have great cauſe to acknowledge that the hand of God was in all this; but I will not on this account any waies turn aſide, but go on as my own heart and conſcience now witneſſeth to me, and I hope the Spirit of God likewiſe; and ſo very deſirous I was to know the meaning of this dark providence, as then it appeared to me to be; that more or leſs for two daies together I often peruſed more of the Book, but my heart was little affected to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular thing, and yet I was troubled more and more within me, and could find no reſt for my poor ſoul; and in leſs than a weeks time, I think about the end of two or three daies, the more I read, I began to have more deep thoughts, and heart amazing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which began to make me exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled, and much caſt down, about the ſtate and condition of my poor captive ſoul, which as I told you before, was almoſt ſunk into the bottom of the bottomleſs Sea of Gods wrath, from which there is no redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, with the weight of its inſupportable ſins; And now what the chief actings of my ſoul were I cannot tell; but ſure I am that my trouble did increaſe yet more and more, and I hope it was for my ſins; for I do well
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:94327:56"/>remember, that within very few dayes, or rather hours after, the ſence of my ſins came into my mind, and the ſight of them was ſo clear, and the number of them ſo numberleſs, and their aggravations ſo weighty, and the nature of them ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, that what I then felt I cannot now poſſibly declare. Oh where was I? certainly had I been ſurprized with the greateſt enemies in the world, and my life in the greateſt danger, I could not have been more troubled, and had I been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with all the tortures that man could have deviſed, I ſhould not have been more tormented; nay, I think if my deceitful heart did not deceive me, that had I been in hell amongſt thoſe infernal fiends, and had heard the yellings and howlings of thoſe damned wretches, I think I could not have been much more affrighted, for then I did look upon my ſoul to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a hairs breadth of Eternal miſery, and oh the condition I ſaw my ſelf then in, is unutterable, had there not been an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting arm of power and mercy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, I ſhould undoubtedly have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſteps of <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Judas;</hi> but O Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and admired be Free Grace: and why Me, Lord, why Me? Oh Love, Love, Love, even Love unſpeakable, yea Love
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:94327:57"/>unutterable; and further, in this my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lord was ſo far pleaſed to pitty and ſhew mercy to my poor ſoul, that my ſoul had not very long laboured under this inſupportable burthen of her great and mighty ſins, but I perceived a door of hope as it were unlatched and ſomewhat open, and that if I would but in good earneſt turn to God, that yet it was not too late, and that there was hope in <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning this thing, which conſideration did not a little comfort my poor ſoul; and then further it pleaſed the Lord to open my heart to viſit one, who I thought might do me much good, and I judged him fit to be acquainted with my condition in that I hoped he feared the Lord, (and by the way let me tell you that I did at that time unſpeakably love all ſuch, even more than my own relations, with humility let it be ſpoken) and when I was with him, he joyfully received me and declared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me many comfortable things, which (through grace) did not a little raiſe my dejected ſpirit, and he then lent me a book, which the Lord at that time opened my heart to aſk for (which was <hi>Drex. d. Eternit.</hi>) and truly upon the peruſal of that Treatiſe, I think, nay I am ſure, the burden of my ſins ſeemed to be renewed,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:94327:57"/>and <hi>I</hi> cannot expreſs that unſpeakable ſorrow which <hi>I</hi> then had in my poor ſoul, by reaſon of all its mighty ſins, and truly <hi>I</hi> hope the mercy of God was not a little cauſe of my trouble, to think that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have none to offend and kick againſt, but thoſe bowels, yea thoſe tender bowels of pitty and compaſſion, which had ſo long yearned over my poor ſoul, and had ſo long ſhielded off the ſtroak of Juſtice, which was ſo long hanging over my provoking head; and then, oh then <hi>I</hi> did unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably deſire the pardon of my ſins, and then did feel the burden of them ſo unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable; that <hi>I</hi> did earneſtly beg of the Lord, that they might be laid upon the Lord Jeſus, who was able to bear them, and did endeavour by earneſt Prayers to obtain a ſmile from God, in and through Jeſus Chriſt; for out of Chriſt he was a terrible God, and a conſuming fire, and ſo <hi>I</hi> forthwith reſolved to take up with all outward duties, as Prayer, Reading, Hearing, Conferring with good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and <hi>I</hi> cannot but let you know that the firſt Sermon <hi>I</hi> heard in this condition was out of 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. where it is ſaid that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of whom <hi>I,</hi> not <hi>Paul</hi> only, but <hi>I</hi> even <hi>I</hi> am chief, and ſo <hi>I</hi> went on through
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:94327:58"/>fear and trembling, and not without ſome joy and hopes that the Lord who had begun a good work in me, would finiſh it in his good time; which God grant for Chriſt his ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>And is this which you have ſpoken from your own experience, is it indeed, as I hope it is, then I can no longer for bear but ſay with good <hi>Zacharias,</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who hath viſited and redeemed his people, and amongſt them thy poor ſoul, and now I ſay again take heed of ſpiritual pride, think very lowly of thy ſelf, and give glory to God: And now (Dear Heart) give me leave for the good of thy eternal welfare to examine thee of ſome things which thou haſt touched upon in the laſt Diſcourſe, that ſo I may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that that work which the Lord hath begun in thee, may prove as a Tree planted and rooted in thy renewed heart, by the Spirit of God, and not of thine own ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And for the accompliſhing of which weighty work, it will be convenient to enquire what fruit it hath ſince born, for the tree may be known by its fruit, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in brief, what haſt thou found in thy heart concerning ſin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Sin! Truly I am not able now to expreſs that unſpeakable bitterneſs I then found in it; oh how did I hate it and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:94327:58"/>it with the greateſt zeal and deteſtation poſſible; oh how did my heart riſe at the very appearance of it, and truly if it did not very greatly deceive me, I think I hated it more than death it ſelf, and ſhould have choſen death rather than wilfully committed the leaſt known ſin; and if there had been no hell, yet as I have often ſaid, ſin ſhould have been my hell, and holineſs my Heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>I am glad to hear what thou haſt ſaid, but what ſins were they thou ſo hatedſt, it may be they were great and dreadful fins, as Blaſphemy and Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but what didſt thou think of heart ſins, and evil motions, which I am ſure would much beſet thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh of I knew my own heart, theſe were the greateſt enemies that I had to encounter; theſe were they that like unto ſo many <hi>Goliahs</hi> bid defiance to what Chriſt had wrought in my poor ſoul, and did endeavour to retake the Fort-Royal of my heart which the Lord was about to make a Temple for his glorious Image to dwell in, and oh Bleſſed be Free Grace, and let all that hear of this, ſtand and admire and give glory to God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord preſerve this bleſſed enmity ſtill more and more in thy heart:
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:94327:59"/>and now tell me which way thou wenteſt about to engage againſt, and ſo to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come theſe great <hi>Goliahs,</hi> though common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known by the name of peccadilloes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh now, now you come very neer me, and this even pierces between the bone and marrow, and the Lord who is the ſearcher of hearts, and knoweth the thoughts and actings of every ſoul, give me underſtanding in this point, that I may ſay nothing but what I really found in my own ſoul; Oh then I did preſume too much upon my own ſtrength, and did not lay them at the feet of Chriſt, whom then I hoped I took for my Lord and King, and did not (as I fear) wholly depend upon his Kingly power, which is to overcome and ſubdue all thoſe enemies which riſe up in the hearts of his Children, and make war againſt him, and would not that he ſhould rule over them, for ſurely had I thus done, he would not have ſuffered them ſo often to aſſault me, and even ſometimes overcome me, as I ſhall (God willing) make clear to you by and by.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Still I have great cauſe to admire the goodneſs of God to thy poor ſoul, in that he hath been pleaſed now to open thy eyes to ſee this thy great miſtake, which doubtleſs had not the Lord in time reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:94327:59"/>it to thee, it would have proved a ſore evil, and it may be thou mighteſt not have ſeen it before it had been too late, and now tell me which way thou wenteſt about to deſtroy thy ſins, ſeeing thou waſt ignorant in great meaſure in applying the death of Chriſt to kill them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>The chiefeſt inſtruments that I uſed in this work was Prayer, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Faſting, which <hi>I</hi> found very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull to batter down the ſtrong holds of Satan in my poor ſoul, for which doubtleſs <hi>I</hi> was not to be blamed, if ſo be that <hi>I</hi> had uſed them only as a means to have raiſed up my heart to Chriſt, and ſo as they were appointed of God to be the way and means whereby <hi>I</hi> might have recourſe to him, who alone is able for ſo great a work, but woe to my ignorant and proud heart, that would not totally ſubmit to God, but idolized Prayer, and Repentance, and Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as if theſe had been the Captains of the ſouls Salvation, whereas they are but empty in themſelves, and nothing worth, no more than as they lead me to Chriſt, who alone is the Captain and horn of my Salvation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>And now <hi>I</hi> think it will not be amiſs to let me hear how you carryed your ſelf in the great duty of Prayer,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:94327:60"/>and how ſoon you entred upon the duty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>The Lord was pleaſed within two or three dayes after my firſt trouble to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline my heart to ſeek him by Prayer, which <hi>I</hi> uſed conſtantly twice a day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome private ejaculations and ſighes between whiles, and <hi>I</hi> will now tell you, that for a little time, about a month or two <hi>I</hi> was little ſatisfied, no longer than <hi>I</hi> was engaged in ſuch work, as Reading, Hearing, deep Meditation, but eſpecially Prayer, and theſe, oh theſe were the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians that <hi>I</hi> look upon ſo much, to work ſo great a cure upon my ſoul, that none but Chriſt that great Phyſitian could do, and truly the beſt of the Phyſitians were ſo full of ill humours themſelves, as pride, ſelf-confidence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that without the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of Chriſts blood to purge and purifie them, they would have ſtunke in the Noſtrills of a holy and pure God, as <hi>I</hi> am afraid they often did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Now you have given in an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count about ſin, <hi>I</hi> would gladly hear what account you can give about the wayes of holineſs and of grace, and how you began to make your progreſs in this road?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> muſt be but very brief here,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:94327:60"/>for <hi>I</hi> have much to ſay about other things, but <hi>I</hi> ſhall, as the Lord ſhall enable me, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you in this, as <hi>I</hi> told you before; when the burthen of my ſin firſt came upon me, that then, and likewiſe in the ſix years of my convictions, <hi>I</hi> was fully convinced of the neceſſity of living a holy life, and of the Beauty of Holineſs, and that without it, there would be no ſalvation; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Holineſs none ſhall ſee the Lord: And upon this account <hi>I</hi> alſo earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord by Prayer, and Hearing, and reading good Books, which the Lord did mightily incline my heart to do, and ſo every day, <hi>I</hi> did more and more deſire Holineſs, and did earneſtly thirſt after the image of God to be renewed upon my heart, ſo that in ſhort <hi>I</hi> found no reſt any way but what <hi>I</hi> got by living holily and abſtaining from ſin, and as my weak Phyſitians, <hi>I</hi> mean my Prayers, Hearing, Reading, Meditation, Vows, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, <hi>&amp;c. I</hi> ſay, as theſe was able to apply comfort to me, ſo <hi>I</hi> had it, and no longer, being ignorant <hi>of the life of Faith in Chriſt,</hi> and truly they proved ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad comforters, and as <hi>I</hi> told you, they wanted Chriſts blood to procure acceptation in the eyes of a pure and holy God, which will regard them with favour,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:94327:61"/>no otherwiſe than as they are preſented to him ſprinkled with the blood of his Son.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks you ſeem to ſpeak much againſt theſe duties, and againſt holineſs, as if they were not altogether neceſſary to be imbraced, do you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>Oh no (God forbid) I hope <hi>I</hi> ſhall never ſo far ſpeak againſt them as to neglect them in the leaſt, but this <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, that <hi>I</hi> may not look upon them any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than as they lead me to Chriſt, for truly <hi>I</hi> have found nothing in the world ſo much hindered me of comfort, (wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſin only excepted) as in laying ſo great a ſtreſs upon duties, for certainly, had <hi>I</hi> laid my foundation ſure upon the Rock of Chriſt, and not all upon my own righteouſneſs, <hi>I</hi> ſhould never have been ſo much ſhaken, and as <hi>I</hi> may ſay almoſt overturned with the aſſaults of ſin and Satan, but he would have upheld me with his everlaſting armes, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have been able long agoe, to have tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed in his merits, over all the aſſaults that Satan and my own heart made againſt me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>How long did you live upon the ſtock of your duties, before the Lord was pleaſed to let you ſee your errour, and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:94327:61"/>how was your condition all this while as you thought your ſelf?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> lived ſo about three years or more, and in that time <hi>I</hi> had ſome ſad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings indeed; every day almoſt <hi>I</hi> loſt my God, and the evidences of his love, ſo as <hi>I</hi> thought my ſelf happy longer than when <hi>I</hi> could perform duties with great zeal and with ſtrong affections, and then oftentimes <hi>I</hi> could have been willing to have dyed (as <hi>I</hi> thought) my heart did ſo rejoyce in them; but when my heart was ſomewhat dead and flat, then <hi>I</hi> was at a great loſs, and could find out no reſt for the ſole of my foot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>This which you have ſaid ſeems to me to be a little ſtrange; why where was your faith all this while? you told me before, that you durſt not look to God but through Chriſt, and you ſeemed then as you went along to make Chriſt your hope and Saviour, and then how do you mean you did not reſt in him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>This is ſomewhat hard to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but <hi>I</hi> hope you will pardon my weakneſs, and <hi>I</hi> will tell you as plain as <hi>I</hi> can, (and that only as my heart and Conſcience witneſſeth, and not to take the help of any book to open it to me,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:94327:62"/>that ſo I may with more humble confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſay that theſe things I have ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> down no otherwiſe but as my own ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit dictated to me) and now I will tell you what I mean by what I have ſaid, I hope I looked upon Chriſt to be a compleat Saviour in every reſpect, and I ſaw my great need of his blood to procure my pardon for my ſins, and I knew that it was only from his grace that I was in any meaſure ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and by this I hope I laid all my ſins upon him, and durſt not in the leaſt think of Anſwering for them my ſelf before God, and ſeemed to give him the glory in reſpect to any work of Holineſs in my heart, and ſo I did highly prize him, and greatly delight in him, and earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to love him, and more and more to ſerve him, and ſo I acted faith for three years, but all this while I was not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced of the inſufficiency of my own righteouſneſs, ſo as to lay that at Chriſts feet, neither could I ſuppoſe it that one might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by anothers righteouſneſs, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that becauſe <hi>I</hi> was not altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as others, (as <hi>I</hi> thought,) there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ould fare better than others, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mixed my own merits with Chriſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never came
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:94327:62"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o far out of my ſelf, as to caſt my righteouſneſs as well as my ſins, at his ſeet, and now what abundant cauſe have <hi>I</hi> to be humbled, and to lye very low before God, and ſtill more and more to admire the infinite mercy and patience of God, Oh that <hi>I</hi> who after <hi>I</hi> was much enlightened, and had abundantly taſted and ſeen how good and gracious the Lord was, <hi>I</hi> ſay that after all his unſpeakable mercies to me, how he brought me out of my Aegyptian bondage of ſin, and looſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me from many ſtrong holds of Satan, and brought me ſo near to his Fathers boſome, that <hi>I</hi> was wont to be many times almoſt raviſhed, with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughts of that joy <hi>I</hi> did hope for in Heaven. Oh that after he had paſſed me over the red Sea, and when many of mine enemies were dead and beaten back, and that after he had tryed me a little in the Wilderneſs of this World, then he would have brought me ſafe into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan;</hi> Oh that <hi>I</hi> ſhould be ſo diſingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to ſet up a Calf (<hi>I</hi> mean my own Righteouſneſs,) and Worſhip that, and ſhould do what <hi>I</hi> did more to advantage ſelf than Chriſt: Oh <hi>I</hi> ſay again, what a wonder it is that ever he was pleaſed to let me ſee my folly; and oh if he ſhould
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:94327:63"/>not have done it, yet in this particular how inexcuſable had <hi>I</hi> been, which will appear in the next Anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Min.</speaker>
               <p>Now let me know when, and in what manner, the Lord was pleaſed to magnifie his grace in convincing you of the inſufficiency of your own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of the reſting in duties.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conv.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> will likewiſe make this as plain to you, as the Lord ſhall enable me (ſo that <hi>I</hi> may not be found guilty of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual lye) and to the beſt of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance about four months after my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful call, when as <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly in a moſt happy condition, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſſed through abundant of tryals and temptations, and <hi>I</hi> began to find them ſomewhat to flee before me, (of which you ſhall hear anon more at large) then, oh then the Lord was pleaſed to put into my hand a little Book, Entituled <hi>The Chriſtians great Intereſt,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Guthry,</hi> which when <hi>I</hi> peruſed, <hi>I</hi> found <hi>I</hi> was much concerned in it, and was ſomewhat troubled, but it ſo violently accuſed me of my <hi>Dalilah</hi> righteouſneſs, which <hi>I</hi> lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too well to ſee as <hi>I</hi> thought abuſed, with a ſmall ſigh or the like, <hi>I</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it to depart, and not to dare to come and controule my idol ſelf any more,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:94327:63"/>yet it made my way ſo plain before me, that <hi>I</hi> could not withſtand it: a little while after, the Lord was pleaſed to put into my hand another Book, for which <hi>I</hi> have abundant cauſe to bleſs God, (which was the <hi>Sincere Convert</hi>) and reading the latter part of that which treats concerning carnal Confidence and reſting in Duties, (all which did very much concern me) <hi>I</hi> was very much troubled, and began to queſtion my eſtate a little concerning duties, but truly <hi>I</hi> took ſo little delight in this, that <hi>I</hi> ſoon laid it by and returned it to the place from whence it came, and likewiſe <hi>I</hi> had other Books as Mr. <hi>Baxters Self-denyal,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> read part of with much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as in reference in denying ſelf-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and ſinful recreations and vain company, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all theſe yielded comfort to me, becauſe <hi>I</hi> found, that <hi>I</hi> did really deſire to deny my ſelf all theſe, and made it a great ground of comfort to me, that <hi>I</hi> could ſo earneſtly deſire their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but when <hi>I</hi> came to the denyal of ſelf-righteouſneſs, this was a hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſelf would not bear it, but away <hi>I</hi> went to thoſe Books where <hi>I</hi> could find out as <hi>I</hi> thought, a way to Heaven by my own working, and thoſe that treated moſt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:94327:64"/>of a holy life, was the moſt pleaſing to me, but when I read concerning Chriſt, or heard him taught to me by his Miniſters; (for although I have omitted how my heart was in hearing, yet I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to include that, and to ſuppoſe that my heart was in that, as in Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Conferring with reſpect to the ſubject) I ſay, when I heard Chriſt taught by his Miniſters, either in a Pulpit or a Book, I much delighted in that I heard or read, but when Juſtification alone by Faith in Chriſts Merits, and living by faith upon a naked Chriſt; (as perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture I might be put too upon a ſick bed, by reaſon of a violent diſeaſe, or the like; that I could not have ſtrength of body nor compoſure of mind to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form duties, as in a Feaver or a fit of the Stone or Gout, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) I ſay when theſe noble and Heaven-born Myſteries were treating on, I was much to ſeek, and could take but little comfort from them, and ſo I went on from duty to duty, and if at any time I found my heart dead, and could for that day or week, or month it may be, find any comfort from them, then I lived in hopes that although I found not all well at preſent, yet it would not long continue ſo with me, and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:94327:64"/>ſo in ſome time <hi>I</hi> recovered life and comfort again, <hi>I</hi> ſay <hi>I</hi> continued thus for the ſpace of above three years; And now <hi>I</hi> will declare one thing which did more trouble me than ordinary, and that was in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, 67. it happened that as <hi>I</hi> was viſiting a patient; (and for this thing in particular <hi>I</hi> have cauſe to bleſs God that he placed me in this my call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) whom we ſuppoſed the Lord would take away, at that very time there came Dr. <hi>B.</hi> to perform as was thought on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the laſt duties he had to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and amongſt his diſcourſe and ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bade her be ſure to lay all her ſins upon Chriſt, which <hi>I</hi> liked very well, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that ſhe ſhould lay all her own Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs at his feet, and not at all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o truſt to any good ſhe had in her ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f, but wholly to rely upon the merits of Chriſt, which when <hi>I</hi> heard, my heart roſe much againſt what he ſaid, and did much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his advice, and thought it not at all convenient to be ſpoken, and doubtleſs had <hi>I</hi> been in her condition (I mean ſo near death as it was thought ſhe was) and he had adviſed me to the ſame thing, and had cleared it to me, oh what a dreadful viſitation had that been, ſurely
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:94327:65"/>it would have put my ſoul into ſuch a dreadful Agony of confuſion, if not deſpair, that ſurely I ſhould have dyed a ſecond death before I knew the pangs of the firſt; But oh I ſay again who can hear of this, and not be overcome with ſoul raviſhing admirations of the love, and goodneſs, and patience of God towards ſuch a wretched nothing as I was; that ever he ſhould ſo long forbear from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying that ſoul with eternal damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that would not with the cords of love be drawn to accept of ſo clear Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but the Lord was pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſed ſtill to keep this upon my heart: And although I was ſomewhat troubled, but as before, again I went to my old Phyſitians, and took a ſmall pill of Prayer, compoſed of a little fear and humiliation; but no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it got into my heart, but there it was guilt with pride, and ſo again became pleaſant to me, and then I thought all was well; and I do deſire earneſtly that by this, God may be much glorified; and again methinks I find my heart ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily inclined to go on in this work, which at your requeſt (you may remember) I was ſo unwilling to undertake, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have great hopes there may be the hand
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:94327:65"/>of God in it, and that it was he that put it into your heart to requeſt if of me, and I pray God it may be his glory alone that may move me to it, and not any ſelf-pride, truly you may ſay I have great cauſe to fear, and not to truſt my own heart any more, and the Lord preſerve this Jealouſie more and more in me: but to my preſent purpoſe, and this which I am about to ſay, might have proved a great diſadvantage to me, but I doubt not but the hand of God was in it, although I ſaw it not at that preſent, but ſince I have, and in ſhort it was thus, a little while after my laſt diſcourſe, as I think my heart was drawn after the vanities of this world more than ordinary, and at the time I likened the eſtate of my ſoul, to the condition of a fair Virgin that had many Suitors, but one ſhe would love and chooſe above the reſt, but ſhe being not yet marryed, they all make out for her love, which is no ſmall trouble to her, and doth ſomewhat make her doubt which ſhe ſhall have; but ſo ſoon as ſhe is marryed to one of them, then ſhe dares not think of entertaining the others upon that account; even ſo I looked upon my poor ſoul, and that if ſhe was but
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:94327:66"/>ſolemnly marryed to Chriſt, (I mean in the Sacrament) then ſhe durſt not ſo much as think of embracing either ſin or the World, or the Devil, but ſtill righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſelf lay all this while ſecure: Upon theſe and ſuch like conſiderations, <hi>I</hi> went to a faithful Divine to ask advice of him concerning this great duty, and when I was with him, he examined me why and how I came to embrace Religion, and when I had given him the heads only of the firſt account concerning compunction, he aſked me who I might thank for all this, but <hi>I</hi> being ſomewhat ſlow of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he told me Chriſt, and him alone, and gave me ſome ſhort but ſweet advice, inviting me to be a gueſt at his Maſters table (which was the intention of my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which was more than he then knew on) and ſo diſmiſſed me, and oh how did I then rejoyce that I was found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be invited to ſo great a banquet, and now how did <hi>I</hi> think my condition unqueſtionable, and nothing troubled me but want of aſſurance to perſevere, and although the <hi>Doctor</hi> gave me a great cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to lay all upon Chriſt and not any thing upon ſelf, as <hi>I</hi> now conſider, but yet my eyes were ſo blind and my heart
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:94327:66"/>ſo deceitful, that I ſoon forgot it; and ſo I prepared my heart as well as I could, and ſo addreſſed my ſelf to the Lords Table, and was, ſo far as I can underſtand, made more welcome, I am ſure than I deſerved; and then I did feel the Lord with his cords of love, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard at my poor ſoul, and ſo I exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed my love upon Chriſt, (and ſo far as I know) enjoyed ſweet communion with him; but this laſted no longer, than my heart was enlarged in ſecret du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but when they departed then my ſoul mourned, and could not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with a naked Chriſt, whileſt my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements returned again to me, and by this I perceive I reſted in duties, and not in Chriſt, and now once more as ſhort as I can, and then I will conclude with this; but I cannot be ſo ſhort, but I muſt a little ſtand and admire at the unſpeakable long-ſuffering patience of God, and oh that you would help me in this matter, for I profeſs I am much aſhamed, and deſire to be more, of my own heart, that it ſhould be barren of praiſes to that God, that hath done ſure as much or more for my poor ſoul, as to any ſince the Creation of the World;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:94327:67"/>Oh that Chriſt who could have raiſed a Child out of the very ſtones, that would have done far more for him than I have or can do; Oh I ſay that he who could with one look have looked me into Hell, ſhould ſo long ſtand at the door of my heart, and knock till his head was filled with dew, and his Locks with the drops of the night; Oh that he ſhould ſtand weeping, knocking, begging, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and crying, Open to me; Oh that his tears ſhould begg, and his groans knock, and that his patience ſhould tarry and wait, and all ſhould ſo long cry, Oh open to me, open to me, Oh that ſin and ſelf ſhould lodge in my heart and Chriſt wait ſo long at the door; Oh, that I ſhould carry damnation within and let ſalvation waite without, and now I ſhould go about to offer praiſes to God for this; Oh I wiſh that I could, but truly I cannot as I would; Oh I cannot, and I humbly deſire to acknowledge the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs of my heart in this, and am ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and now pray lend me your patience but a very little, and I fear your heart will be ſtraightened with praiſes to God as well as mine; for now the Lord was pleaſed to encline my heart to read part
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:94327:67"/>of two books, one of the two was that which I above two years before rejected, I will name them (<hi>viz.</hi> the ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and ſound Believer, both by one Author, <hi>T. S.</hi>) and when I was Reading concerning the ſouls reſting in duties, and how hard a thing it was to forſake all its own good, and wholly to throw it ſelf upon a naked Chriſt, and then concerning the nature of true humiliation, I was much troubled and my thoughts were much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, in ſo much that I thought to open my caſe to ſome Divine; but to this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble another was added, which was that at that time the Lord was pleaſed to let me ſee my own nakedneſs ſo much, and that which I took to be a covering to it, made it ſeem to be much more naked than I could have imagined it to be; that then I thought the more I prayed, the more I ſinned, and the more I Confeſſed and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and Bewailed my own wretched heart, eſpecially in the time of duty, the more I had cauſe to do ſo ſtill, and now I looked upon my ſelf in a moſt ſad and deſtitute condition, for how could <hi>I</hi> chooſe when I ſaw my own goodneſs departing from me, which I idolized as the rock of my Salvation, and when I ſaw ſuch a
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:94327:68"/>numberleſs number of ſins come afreſh into my mind, eſpecially in the time of duty, that it ſeemed to me, as if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil had conjured up all thoſe ſins that <hi>I</hi> thought was long before ſlain, and he himſelf had been their Captain, and had unawares aſſaulted me, and had taken my duty which <hi>I</hi> made then the Captain of my Salvation priſoner, and <hi>I</hi> alone left to encounter with them without the leaſt weapon to defend my poor ſoul, and oh had theſe and the pangs of death met together, Oh what horrour and amazement would there have been; but bleſſed be God it was before; now to ſay, how long I was in this caſe, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well tell; but <hi>I</hi> ſaw my idol God ſo accuſed and condemned, and my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to him was ſo great, that <hi>I</hi> hope <hi>I</hi> did deſire never to ceaſe my earneſt Prayers to the true God, that he would 01 have this uſurper executed, and likewiſe <hi>I</hi> did, as <hi>I</hi> was able, earneſtly begg of the Lord that he would give me ſtrength to reſiſt him ſo that he might never ſit upon his Throne more, and then <hi>I</hi> did ſee (through admiring Grace) the want of Chriſt more than ever, not only to cover my ſins, but my righteouſneſs too;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:94327:68"/>then oh then <hi>I</hi> began to prize Chriſt more than ever, oh then <hi>I</hi> did deſire to ſay from my heart none but Chriſt, none but Chriſt; oh all the whole world for Chriſt, yea ten thouſand Worlds for a Chriſt; and then <hi>I</hi> did deſire to ſay with <hi>Luther,</hi> that if <hi>I</hi> was able to keep the whole Moral Law, I would not truſt to this for Juſtification, <hi>I</hi> would vail and ſtoop to Chriſts merits, and now I did find it a more hard thing by far, to get out of my ſelf, and from truſting to duty, and wholly by faith to rely upon Chriſts merits, than ever I found it to leave ſin, and then me-thoughts <hi>I</hi> found it a very hard thing to be a Chriſtian, and that I was paſſive all along and was not able to move a ſtep further than the Lord up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and led me, and oh that <hi>I</hi> could make the reſult of this great mercy plain unto you, truly (<hi>I</hi> bleſs God) I can ſay a little (but under this very trouble, my ſoul ever ſince hath groaned within me, and I do deſire that it may ſtill groan more and more, and never leave groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till its groans pierce the very clouds, and found through Chriſt ſo loud into the ears of the Almighty, that for Chriſt his ſake, he would have pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:94327:69"/>upon me, and would not ſuffer that Tyrant Self any longer in the leaſt to bear ſway in me, and that he would be pleaſed ſo to ſhew me my own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, and the inſufficiency of all inherent goodneſs to ſtand me in the leaſt ſtead in matters of Juſtification, that ſo <hi>I</hi> might prize Chriſt and Chriſt alone, and rely wholly upon his merits for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, life and ſalvation.) Now I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to you how the Lord was pleaſed to deal with me; ſoon after I ſaw this my condition in reſting in my own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed goodneſs; Sacrament day being again near at hand, the Lord was pleaſed to incline my heart to ingage in that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and moſt Sacred duty, now having loſt my ſuppoſed wedding garment, in which I ſuppoſed my ſelf to be very come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and much to be delighted in by Chriſt, and ſeeing my own nakedneſs and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſo much, that I could not imagine how I ſhould poſſibly be accepted of by Chriſt, that ſo my trouble and burden was ſo great that I found it almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, and fearing leſt Gods frowns and my awakened Conſcience ſhould more and more ſeiſe upon me, eſpecially at that ſacred ordinance, I ſay in this point
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:94327:69"/>I was more than I can think of amazed, and could not tell what to do; And now my dear Heavenly Father (who was alwayes more ready to help than I to crave) did then doubtleſs wait to be gracious to my poor ſoul, and did abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly magnifie his grace to me; for now he was pleaſed to ſtrike one Scripture very deep into my heart, which was as comfortable and as ſure an Anchor as my poor laden ſoul could be held by, and it was this, <hi>Oh Iſrael thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, but in me is thy help,</hi> Hoſea 13.9. which ſoul-cordial Scripture ſeemed to me, as if I had heard the Lord ſpeaking to me after this manner; oh thou afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, toſted with tempeſt and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, although thou haſt ſo long griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and provoked me to deſtroy thee, yet now, even now, if thou wilt endeavour to know, I ſay even now in this thy day the things of thy peace, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture they may be found, but never look more for peace from any thing in thy ſelf, but wholly look up to him, who tells thee, although thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thy ſelf, yet in me (if in any) is thy help found, and then further the Lord was pleaſed to put it into my heart
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:94327:70"/>to examine my humiliation more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which when I did, I ſuppoſed my heart never heretofore to have been truly humbled as it ought to have been, yet I hoped the Lord was about this great work now, by what I have before related, and my reaſon was, becauſe I never ſo far as I knew experimentally underſtood the meaning of ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as then were opened more plainly to me, and they were ſuch as theſe; (And truly this was it that inclined my heart to partake afreſh of the Lords Supper) The whole need not a Phyſitian but they that are ſick, and That Chriſt came not to call the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous but Sinners to Repentance, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Publican and Phariſee, and ſuch like; and in ſhort, although I had been ſick of ſin, yet never before, than of ſelf-righteouſneſs; now ſeeing my ſelf ſick as much of the one as of the other, therefore I hoped Chriſt would be my Phyſitian; and that in him my help ſhould ſoon be found, and thus I did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to humble my ſelf, and to ſee my own vileneſs and ſickneſs more and more, and did in this much begg of the Lord, that he would ſtill humble me more and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:94327:70"/>more, with a clear ſence of my own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie and nakedneſs, that ſo I might, ſeeing my great need of Chriſt, more and more hunger and thirſt after him, and ſo laying my ſoul proſtrated at Chriſts feet, and as I hope did really ſee my great want of him, and ſo would not depart any way from him, but reſolved that if I dyed <hi>I</hi> would dye there, and thus I argued with him, Whither ſhould I go but unto thee, thou haſt the words of eternal life, and although I be a dog, yet thou haſt crumbs, oh let not my hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry ſoul, famiſh for want of food; Oh I dare not, oh I will not depart, oh Lord although I have deſtroyed my ſelf, yet Lord haſt not thou told me that in thee is my help found; oh make good thy word unto thy ſervant in which thou haſt cauſed me to hope; and truly the Lord was not very long in making good his word to my poor ſoul, for then I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully felt him drawing me up with the Cords of love, pitty and compaſſion; and at the ends of which cords (for me to take the better hold, or I rather think that he might take the better hold of me) he was pleaſed to faſten ſuch Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures as theſe, I will name but three,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:94327:71"/>for each cord one, and a threefold cord is not eaſily broken: the one was the 55th. of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the firſt verſe, <hi>Hoe every one that thirſteth, come ye to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and drink, and he that hath no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> yea that was it I waited for, (for I bleſs God at that time I hope I had none) <hi>come ye buy and eat, yea come buy Wine and Milk</hi> (oh Bread and Water was too good for me and more than I deſerved) <hi>without money, and without price,</hi> Oh theſe was ſweet to ſuch a poor ſoul as mine was, and then another was this, Revel. 22.17. <hi>And whoſoever will, let him take of the water of life freely,</hi> hearken ſoul, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Oh Chriſt will not be bought with any thing the Creature can give, oh no all is grace, and then the other which worked the moſt powerfully upon my heart was Matth. 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt;</hi> and therefore, I now ſeeing my ſelf weary with my own du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and heavy laden with my own Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, as well as with my ſins, which before I could not ſo clearly ſay, oh how ſweet, how ſweet, how incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſweet was this word Come; and ſo upon theſe accounts, the Lord was pleaſed
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:94327:71"/>to enable me, to ſee how, then, even then, he was pleaſed to call, as it were to my poor ſoul in particular to come unto him and ſubmit to his grace; and ſo with great hungrings and thirſtings after Chriſt to cover my poor ſoul from the eye of a juſt and holy God through ſome fear, and as I hope with great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation (although not ſo great as I would have had it) with ſome hope that the Lord would meet me, and bleſs me: I approached to the ſolemn banquet where I did not only taſte and ſip a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but obeyed as the Lord enabled me that great command when he ſaid, drink, yea drink abundantly, oh my beloved; then, oh then I did earneſtly endeavour to make the eye of my ſoul ſo ſee him, and my heart ſo embrace him, that from thenceforth I might fully ſatisfie my ſoul with the enjoyment of him, and him alone, and not from any thing that ſelf or the World preſented to me; and now me-thought I was much comforted, and did endeavour from that time to this, to own nothing for a comfort or cauſe of rejoycing, but as it lead me to Chriſt, who alone is the Author, and I hope the finiſher of my Faith, and the Horn
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:94327:72"/>of my Salvation; and with this Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will conclude this tedious diſcourſe as I fear it may be to you (although to me through Grace very pleaſant) not that hereby I mean to neglect any duty whatſoever I know to be my duty, or think them indifferent whether they be performed or no; oh no I ſay again God forbid, but this I deſire to do through grace, but not ſelf, (and the Lord of his infinite grace inable me, that I may ſo far honour and reſpect them, as I find them a means to carry me to Chriſt,) for which cauſe I think they were appointed, with reſpect to the glorifying of God, and ſuch like; and now if I know my own heart, and for fear it ſhould deceive me, I will begg of the Lord that whenever I hear <hi>I</hi> may hear for Chriſt, and whenever I pray I may more and more make clear my intereſt in Chriſt, and whenever I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any duty whatſoever, I may more and more get into Chriſt and more out of my ſelf; And now you have heard all that the Lord hath (out of his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace) enabled me (from what I have found, as I hope in great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure wrought in my own heart) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you, and for fear I ſhould
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:94327:72"/>in this weighty matter be guilty of a lye and ſo delude my own ſoul, I will with great humility acknowledge, that every particular in this latter clauſe (I mean in the Lords dealings with me ſince I firſt received the Sacrament) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo fully clear as I would I could, but I hope I need not to fear, but that I have felt all that I have ſpoken of working more or leſs upon my heart: but whether juſt in order as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared them, I cannot punctually ſay, but do earneſtly begg that the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt would be ſo pleaſed, as to ſprinkle what I have ſaid with his own blood, and that whatever ſins of fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings there may be in it through the pride or ignorance of my own heart, oh I do earneſtly again beg of God, that for Chriſts ſake, he would look upon what I have done ſo as to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all that is amiſs, and that he would in his due time open my eyes to ſee my errours and to amend them; and now I do earneſtly beg your advice concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, for as I ſaid before, my heart doth mourn within me, by reaſon of that intereſt ſelf got in me, and I now find it ſo very hard to be
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:94327:73"/>overcome; but I have already told you my earneſt deſires concerning this, and oh that I could prevail with you this once to allow me an intereſt in your Prayers, and for what doubtleſs you will know better than <hi>I</hi> can tell you, but eſpecially for this, that he. who is the ſearcher of hearts, and knows the ſtate of every ſoul better than it doth it ſelf, would be pleaſed that if <hi>I</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for Chriſts ſake to undeceive me, and grant that if <hi>I</hi> have not true grace, <hi>I</hi> may not think <hi>I</hi> have, and ſo be in a Fools Paradice, and that the Lord who is my heart maker, would be my heart ſearcher, and my heart diſcoverer, and my heart reformer, and that the Lord may ſo do, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not ceaſe to be an earneſt ſuitor at the Throne of grace ſo long as I am on this ſide the grave. But what, becauſe all is not ſo clear as <hi>I</hi> could wiſh they were, ſhall I be caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and my ſoul diſquieted within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> if <hi>I</hi> was ſorry that God hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> at work in my ſoul, or as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jeho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> was not able to finiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he hath begun, and ſo rob God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glory, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my poor ſoul of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, theſe things ought
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:94327:73"/>not ſo to be, <hi>I</hi> fear-there is much of ſelf in this who is ſomewhat troubled to ſee the glory of its Temple ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, and its treachery ſo much found out, and ſo much out of Favour, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more to be embraced again; And is it ſo, is God indeed become my God, and can <hi>I</hi> indeed ſay with <hi>Thomas, My Lord, and my God, my Chriſt, and my Saviour;</hi> Oh I cannot forbear to ſay, Lord who is a God like unto thee, Oh God, there is no God beſides thee, and oh what is man that God ſhould be mindfull of him! and what am I, ſurely the worſt of men, that God ſhould ſo regard me; Oh that <hi>I</hi> could now, even now this once from the bottom of my heart, bleſs and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire him; but oh what a dead and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren heart have <hi>I,</hi> that cannot worthily praiſe him; Oh my ſoul bleſs the Lord, and all that is within me, bleſs his holy name, bleſs the Lord oh my ſoul, and forget not all (nay not one of) his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits: oh if I had the tongue of an Angel, and all the Angels in Heaven to aſſiſt me in this great work, yet <hi>I</hi> ſay, we could never ſufficiently utter my dear fathers praiſes; and now ſhall my faith triumph, and my heart be glad,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:94327:74"/>and my glory rejoyce, but not in ſelf, or in any thing of my own, but in him, and him alone who is the God of my Salvation; Wonder oh Heavens, and be moved oh earth at this great thing which the Lord hath wought in my ſoul, be aſtoniſhed and even raviſhed with wonder, for the infinite breach is in a way to be made up, the offender to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, and God and my poor ſoul to be reconciled; and oh my ſoul, what if theſe be ſo already, or what if one had told thee of theſe things ſome five years agone, certainly they would then have been too great for thy belief; but what, ſhall they now be ſo ſmall as not to be worth thy praiſe (oh diſingenious ſoul:) Oh Lord pardon my unthankfulneſs; oh that all the Angels in Heaven ſhould rejoyce and bleſs God for what he hath done for thee, even for thee, for my poor ſoul; And what, canſt not thou find in heart to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſet forth his praiſes as much as thou art able, that ſo it may be known that at leaſt thou deſireſt to give all the glory to God, and not to dare to take any to thy ſelf? oh my ſoul, what ſayeſt thou? What ſay <hi>I?</hi> oh <hi>I</hi> ſay again not unto me, not unto me, but unto the great
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:94327:74"/>and glorious <hi>Jehovah</hi> be all the glory given. And becauſe I hope thy deſires are greater than thy expreſſions, therefore fail not my ſoul to ſhew forth thy love and praiſes, by giving up thy ſelf wholly to ſerve, and love, fear and admire that God, who hath done ſuch great and wonderful things for thy ſoul that paſſeth thy underſtanding: My Beloved is mine, and <hi>I</hi> am his; oh how art thou ſure of that? What is the peace concluded? oh happy Concluſion! oh bleſſed Conjunction! ſhall the Stars dwell with the duſt, or the wide diſtant Poles be brought to mutual embraces, and co-habitation? but oh my ſoul, here the diſtance is infinitely greater? And now Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce O Angels, ſhout O Seraphims, and all the friends of the Bridegroom prepare an Epithalamium, be ready with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Song; loe here is the wonder of wonders, For <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath or is about to betroth himſelf for ever to his poor Captive, my poor ſoul; And is he ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as <hi>I</hi> hope he is, then he owns the Marriage before all the World, and is become one with me, and <hi>I</hi> with him. And now, O my Lord and my God, cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thy face to ſhine on the ſoul of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and ſhew him more and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:94327:75"/>vileneſs that he may lye very low even in the Duſt, and be humbled at thy feet, and let the work which thou haſt begun in the heart of thy poor Servant be eſtabliſhed for ever, and do more for me than I can require, that thy name may be Magnified for ever, and that all that hear of this may ſay, The Lord of Hoſts is the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>
               <hi>Amen, Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:94327:75"/>
            <head>Theſe Books, with ſeveral others, are Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and to be ſold by <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the Chirurgions Arms in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> near the Hoſpital-Gate.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>A Relation in form of a Journal, of the Voyage, and Reſidence of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Holland.</hi> By Sir <hi>William Lower,</hi> Knight.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Memoires,</hi> of the Lives, Actions, Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Deaths of thoſe noble, Reverend Perſonages that ſuffered by Death, Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, Decimation, or otherwiſe for the Proteſtant Religion, and the Great Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereof. By <hi>David Lloyd, A. M.</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of <hi>Oriel</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> his Hiſtory of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of Juſtification. By <hi>George Downam,</hi> Doctor of Divinity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spencers</hi> Hiſtory of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brathwaits</hi> Engliſh Gentleman and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94327:76"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Auſtins Meditations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Review of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Babingtons</hi> Works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jermin</hi> on the <hi>Proverbs</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>THat Excellent Piece of Mr. <hi>George Swinnocks</hi> Chriſtian-mans Calling, in three Volumns, Directing the Chriſtian how to make Religion his Buſineſs in all Relations, Conditions, and Occurrences that may fall out in his whole life.</item>
               <item>Faiths Univerſal Uſefulneſs, with the Excellency of a Spiritual Life. By that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous man of God, Maſter <hi>Matthew Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Elborough</hi>'s Sermon on the Fire.</item>
               <item>There is now extant that much expected Book of Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Burroughs,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Goſpel Remiſſion:</hi> Wherein is diſcovered, Firſt, the many and great Goſpel-Myſteries therein contained. Secondly, the glorious effects proceeding from it. Thirdly, the miſtakes that are made about it. Fourthly, the true Signs and Symptomes of it. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the way and means how to obtain it.</item>
               <item>The Virtue and Value of Baptiſm Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chetically propounded as Antidote againſt all Baptiſm-deſpiſing Dicrates. By Mr. <hi>Zach. Crof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94327:76"/>
               <item>That much expected Piece of Mr. <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Scotland,</hi> his Expoſition upon the whole Book of <hi>Canticles,</hi> or <hi>Song of solomon,</hi> is now Printed, with Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> Preface, and Mr. <hi>Durhams</hi> Epiſtle.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Hamptons</hi> Sermon before King <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leſley</hi>'s Sermon tending to Unity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hampton</hi>'s Three-fold State of man.</item>
               <item>A Sermon before King <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſtory of the Gentle Craft.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dod</hi> and <hi>Clever</hi> on the Commandments.</item>
               <item>Souls Sentinels.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spicers</hi> Elogie on Sir <hi>Arthur Cheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe upon Prodigious Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence: Occaſioned by the Twelve Moneths Faſting of <hi>Martha Taylor,</hi> the Famed <hi>Derby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> Damoſel: Proving that without any Miracle, the Texture of Humane Bodies may be ſo altered, that Life may be long Continued without the ſupplies of Meat and Drink. With an Account of the Heart, and how far it is intereſſed in the Buſineſs of Fermentation. Humbly offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Royal Society. By <hi>John Reynolds.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Quakers <hi>Spiritual Court</hi> Proclaim'd. Being an exact Narrative of two ſeveral Tryals had before that <hi>New-High-Court of Juſtice,</hi> at the <hi>Pcele</hi> in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Street; To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Names of the Judges that ſate in Judgement, and of the Parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb facs="tcp:94327:77"/>in the ſaid Tryals: Alſo ſundry Errors and Corruptions, in Principle and Practice among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which were never till now made known to the World. Alſo a <hi>Direction</hi> to attain to be a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and Profit by it. All which, with many new matters and things of Remark among thoſe Men; are faithfully declared and teſtified. By <hi>Nathaniel Smith</hi> Student in Phyſick, who was himſelf a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and converſant among them for the ſpace of about XIV. Years.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo.</head>
               <item>THe Life of Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. With the Remarks upon thoſe Times, not unworthy the peruſal of ours.</item>
               <item>The Excellency of the Pen and Penſil, exemplifying the Uſes of them in the moſt Exquiſite and Myſterious Arts of Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Etching, Engraving, Limbning, Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Oyl, waſhing Maps and Pictures: Alſo the way to cleanſe any old Painting, and preſerve the Colours: Furniſhed with divers Copper Cuts.</item>
               <item>A guide to Ladies, Gentlewomen, and Maids, how to behave themſelves in all Eſtates, Relations and Conditions. By <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah Wolley.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94327:77"/>
               <item>A guide to the True Religion, Direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to make a wiſe Choice of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion men Venture their Salvation upon. By <hi>J. Clapham,</hi> M.A.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtians great Intereſt, or a ſhort Treatiſe divided into two Parts, The firſt whereof containeth the Tryal of a Saving Intereſt in Chriſt. The ſecond pointeth forth plainly the way how to obtain it; wherein ſomewhat is likewiſe ſpoken to the manner of Expreſs Covenanting with God. By <hi>W. Guthry,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Fifth Impreſſion.</item>
               <item>Juſtification only upon a Satisfaction; or the Neceſſity and Verity of the Satisfaction of Chriſt, as the alone ground of Remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin, aſſerted and opened againſt the Socinians. By <hi>Robert Fergirſon,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Paſtors Love to a Loving People. By Mr. <hi>William Thompſon,</hi> Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Synopſis</hi> of Quakariſme, or a Collection of the Fundamental Errors of the Quakers.</item>
               <item>With a brief Refutation of their moſt Material Arguments (and particularly <hi>W. Pen</hi>'s in his late <hi>Sandy Foundation ſhaken</hi>) and an Eſſay toward the Eſtabliſhment of private Chriſtians in the Truth oppoſed by thoſe Errors. By <hi>Thomas Danſon,</hi> ſometime
<pb facs="tcp:94327:78"/>Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Laws and Canons drawn up, and agreed upon by the General Aſſembly or Meeting of the Head of the Quakers from all parts of the Kingdom.</item>
               <item>Phanatick Primer for the Inſtruction of Little Ones, in order to perfect reading. By <hi>H. Adis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rebukes for ſin by Gods Burning Anger, by the burning of the City, the burning of World, and the burning of the Wicked; with a Diſcourſe of Heart-fixedneſs. By <hi>Thomas Doolittel,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>The Life of Dr. <hi>James Uſher,</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Primate of all <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A moſt Comfortable and Chriſtian Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. By Mr. <hi>William Cooper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spare Minutes: Or Reſolved Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and premeditated Reſolutions. By <hi>Arthur Warwick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clariſſimi Viri Adriani Heerchoordi Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophiae profeſſoris Ordinarii Diſputationum de Concurſu Examen a Johanne Stearne M.D. Inſtitutum ad Amicum ſuum Johannem Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Excellent Oration of that late fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly Learned <hi>John Raynolds,</hi> D. D. and Lecturer of the Greek Tongue in <hi>Oxford,</hi> very uſeful for all ſuch as affect the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb facs="tcp:94327:78"/>of Logick and Philoſophy, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Profane Learning.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Archers</hi> Jeſts.</item>
               <item>Heaths Tranſubſtantiation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sejanus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Owen</hi>'s Epigrams.</item>
               <item>King <hi>James</hi> meditations.</item>
               <item>None but Chriſt.</item>
               <item>Four Select Sermons upon ſeveral Texts of Scripture, wherein the Idolatry and Will-worſhip of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is laid open and confuted. By Mr. <hi>Will. Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar</hi> of <hi>Rochſord,</hi> never before publiſhed.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>James Maltons</hi> twenty Sermons preached on ſeveral Texts, <hi>viz.</hi> Mans Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and Gods Compaſſion ſhewed, on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 138.3.</item>
               <item>Mercy deſpiſed, and God provoked thereby on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106.24.</item>
               <item>Chriſts Pretiouſneſs, on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</item>
               <item>The neceſſity of Humiliation, on <hi>Acts</hi> 16.29, 30.</item>
               <item>Chriſt the Bread of Life, on <hi>John</hi> 6.35.</item>
               <item>Chriſts two Diſciples doers of Gods will, on <hi>John</hi> 7.17.</item>
               <item>Fear of loſing Salvation, and the way to obtain it, on <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1.</item>
               <item>The Perſevering Saint ſhall be crowned Saint, on <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11.</item>
               <item>Walking in Chriſt a ſign of our right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Chriſt, on <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:94327:79"/>
               <item>Light Diſcovered, and Man Recovered, on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10.</item>
               <item>Chriſts Temptation, the Saints Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, on <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. and the laſt Verſe.</item>
               <item>Chriſts proviſion for mans Direction, on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.11.</item>
               <item>Heaven upon Earth, or the Beſt Friend in the Worſt Times. By <hi>James Janeway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Unhappy Proſperity expreſſed in the Hiſtory of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lius Sejanus,</hi> and <hi>Philippa</hi> the <hi>Catamian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Practice of Quietneſs, directing a Chriſtian how to live quietly in this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome World.</item>
               <item>The CHURCH MILITANT, Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally continued from the Year 33. to the Year 1640. By Sir <hi>William Vaughan,</hi> Knight.</item>
               <item>A moſt Comfortable and Chriſtian DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ALOGUE between the Lord and the Soul. By <hi>William Cooper,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Galloway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Vertue, Vigour, and Efficacy of the Promiſes Diſplayed in their Strength and Glory. Duly methodiſed, and fitly applyed to every Chriſtians particular Caſe and Condition. In a <hi>Soliloquy,</hi> wholly Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, between the <hi>Soul</hi> and the <hi>Comforter</hi> With a Divine Rapture of the <hi>Soul,</hi> now reſting ſatisfied by the Spirit of the <hi>Holy Promiſe.</hi> By <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Henderſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hollingworths</hi> Juſtification. In <hi>Duodecimo</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94327:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
